<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ब्रह्मौदनं᳘ पचति॥
रे᳘त एव त᳘द्धत्ते यदा᳘ज्यमुछिष्य᳘ते ते᳘न रशना᳘मभ्यज्या᳘दत्ते ते᳘जो वाऽआ᳘ज्यं प्राजापत्यो᳘ऽश्वः प्रजा᳘पतिमेव ते᳘जसा स᳘मर्धयत्य᳘पूतो वा᳘ऽएॗषोऽमेध्यो यद᳘श्वः॥
Eggeling He (the Adhvaryu) cooks the priests’ mess of rice 1: it is seed he thereby produces. Having greased a rope with the ghee which is left over 2, he takes it; for ghee is (a type of) fiery spirit, and the horse is sacred to Prajāpati 3: he thus endows Prajāpati with fiery spirit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber व्यृद्धमु वा᳘ऽएत᳘द्यज्ञ᳘स्य॥
य᳘दयजु᳘ष्केण क्रिय᳘तऽइमा᳘मगृम्णन्रशना᳘मृतस्ये᳘त्यश्वाभिधा᳘नीमा᳘दत्ते य᳘जुष्कृत्यै यज्ञ᳘स्य स᳘मृद्ध्यै द्वा᳘दशारत्निर्भवति द्वा᳘दश मा᳘साः संवत्सरः᳘ संवत्सर᳘मेव᳘ यज्ञ᳘माप्नोति॥
Eggeling Now, unsuccessful in the sacrifice, assuredly, is what is performed without a formula. (With Vāj. S. XXII, 2,) &amp;lsquo;This rope did they take, at the first age of the truth, [the sages, at the rites: it hath been with us at this Soma-sacrifice, declaring the course in the gaining of the truth],&amp;rsquo; he takes the halter of the horse in order to supply a formula for the success of the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘था वै᳘ हविषो᳘ऽहुतस्य स्क᳘न्देत् ॥
एव᳘मेत᳘त्पशो᳘ स्कन्दति यं᳘ निक्तम᳘नालब्धमुत्सृज᳘न्ति य᳘त्स्तोकी᳘या जुहो᳘ति सर्वहु᳘तमेॗवैनं जुहोत्य᳘स्कन्दाया᳘स्कन्नᳫं हि तद्य᳘द्धुत᳘स्य स्क᳘न्दति सह᳘स्रं जुहोति सह᳘स्रसंमितो वै᳘ स्वर्गो᳘ लोकः᳘ स्वर्ग᳘स्य लोक᳘स्याभि᳘जित्यै ॥
Eggeling Even as some of the havis (offering-material) may be spilled before it is offered, so also (part) of the victim is here spilled in that they let loose the sprinkled (horse) before it is slain. When he offers the Stokīyās (oblations of drops), he offers that (horse) as a complete offering 1&amp;ndash;so as to make good any spilling 2; for unspilled is any (part) of the offered (material) that is spilled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरश्वमेध᳘मसृजत᳟᳟॥
सोऽस्मात्सृष्टः प᳘राङैत्स दि᳘शोऽनुप्रा᳘विशत्तं᳘ देवाः प्रै᳘षमैछंस्तमि᳘ष्टिभिरनुप्रा᳘युञ्जत तमि᳘ष्टिभिर᳘न्वैछंस्तमि᳘ष्टिभिर᳘न्वविन्दन्यदि᳘ष्टिभिर्य᳘जते᳘ऽश्वमेव तन्मे᳘ध्यं य᳘जमानो᳘ऽन्विछति ॥
Eggeling Prajāpati poured forth the life-sap of the horse (aśva-medha) 1. When poured forth, it went straight away from him and spread itself over the regions. The gods went in quest of it. By means of offerings (ishṭi) they followed it up, by offerings they searched for it, and by offerings they found it. And when he performs ishṭis, the Sacrificer thereby searches for the horse (aśva) meet for sacrifice 2 (medhya).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘प वा᳘ एत᳘स्मात्॥
श्री᳘ राष्ट्रं᳘ क्रामतिॗ योऽश्वमेधे᳘न य᳘जते यदा वै पु᳘रुषः श्रि᳘यं ग᳘छति वी᳘णास्मै वाद्यते ब्राह्मणौ᳘ वीणागाथि᳘नौ संवत्सरं᳘ गायतः श्रियै वा᳘ एत᳘द्रूपं यद्वी᳘णा श्रि᳘यमेॗवास्मिंस्त᳘द्धत्तः॥
Eggeling But, indeed, distinction, royal sway, departs from him who performs the horse-sacrifice; and when a man attains to distinction, the lute is played to him. Two Brāhmaṇical lute-players sing (and play) for a year; for that&amp;ndash;to wit, the lute&amp;ndash;is a form (attribute) of distinction: it is distinction they thus confer upon him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/6/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber विभू᳘र्मात्रा᳘ प्रभूः᳘ पित्रे᳘ति॥
इयं वै᳘ माॗतासौ᳘ पिॗताभ्यामेॗवैनम् प᳘रिददात्य᳘श्वोऽसि ह᳘योऽसी᳘ति शा᳘स्त्येॗवैनं तत्त᳘स्माछिष्टाः᳘ प्रजा᳘ जायन्ते᳘ऽत्योऽसि म᳘योऽसीत्य᳘त्येॗवैनं नयति त᳘स्माद᳘श्वः पशूनां श्रै᳘ष्ठ्यं गछत्य᳘र्वासि स᳘प्तिरसि वाज्यसी᳘ति यथायजु᳘रेॗवैतद्वृ᳘षासि नृम᳘णा असी᳘ति मिथुनत्वा᳘य य᳘युर्ना᳘मासि शि᳘शुर्ना᳘मासी᳘त्येतद्वा अ᳘श्वस्य प्रियं᳘ नामधे᳘यम् प्रिये᳘णैॗवैनं ना᳘म्नाभि᳘वदति त᳘स्माद᳘प्यामित्रौ᳘ संग᳘त्य ना᳘म्ना चे᳘दभिव᳘दतोॗऽन्योऽन्यᳫं स᳘मेव᳘ जानाते॥
Eggeling [The Adhvaryu and Sacrificer whisper in the right ear of the horse, Vāj. S. XXII, 19 1,] &amp;lsquo;Plenteous by the mother, strengthful by the father,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;its mother, doubtless, is this (earth), and its father yonder (sky): it is to these two he commits it;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;a horse thou art, a steed thou art,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;he thereby instructs it, whence clever subjects (or children) are born to him;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;a courser (atya) thou art, a charger thou art,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;he therewith leads it beyond (ati), whence the horse goes beyond (surpasses) other animals, and whence the horse attains to pre-eminence among animals;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;a runner thou art, a racer thou art, a prize-winner thou art,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;in accordance with the text is (the meaning of) this;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;a male thou art, well-disposed towards man thou art,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;this is with a view to its (or, his) being supplied with a mate;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Speedy thou art called, Child thou art called,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;this is the horse&amp;rsquo;s favourite name: by its favourite name he thus addresses it; whence even if two enemies 2, on meeting together, address one another by name, they get on amicably together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/7/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरकामयत॥
अश्वमेधे᳘न यजेये᳘तिॗ सोऽश्राम्यत्स त᳘पोऽतप्यत त᳘स्य श्रान्त᳘स्य तप्त᳘स्य सप्तॗधात्म᳘नो 1 देव᳘ता अ᳘पाक्रामन्त्सा᳘ दीॗक्षाभवत्स᳘ एता᳘नि वैश्वदेवा᳘न्यपश्यत्ता᳘न्यजुहोत्तैर्वै स᳘ दीक्षाम᳘वारुन्द्ध य᳘द्वैश्वदेवा᳘नि जुहो᳘ति दीक्षा᳘मेव तैर्य᳘जमानो᳘ऽवरुन्द्धेऽन्वहं᳘ जुहोत्यन्वह᳘मेव᳘ दीक्षाम᳘वरुन्द्धे सप्त᳘ जुहोति सप्त वै ता᳘ देव᳘ता अ᳘पाक्रामंस्ता᳘भिरेॗवास्मै दीक्षाम᳘वरुन्द्धे॥
Eggeling Prajāpati desired, &amp;lsquo;Might I perform a horse-sacrifice 2?&amp;rsquo; He toiled and practised fervid devotion. From the body of him, when wearied and heated, the deities departed in a sevenfold way: therefrom the Dīkshā (initiation) was produced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/8/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरश्वमेध᳘मसृजत॥
स᳘ सृष्टः प्र᳘र्चम᳘व्लीनात्प्र सा᳘म तं᳘ वैश्वदेवान्यु᳘दयछन्य᳘द्वैश्वदेवा᳘नि जुहो᳘त्यश्वमेध᳘स्यैवो᳘द्यत्यै॥
Eggeling Prajāpati poured forth the life-sap of the horse 1. When poured forth, it weighed down the r̥c (hymn-verse) and the sāman (hymn-tune). The Vaiśvadeva (offerings) upheld that (Aśvamedha): thus, when he offers the Vaiśvadevas, it is for the upholding of the Aśvamedha. ०२ मूलम् - Weber का᳘य स्वा᳘हा॥
क᳘स्मै स्वा᳘हा कतम᳘स्मै स्वाहे᳘ति प्राजापत्यम् मु᳘ख्यं करोति प्रजा᳘पतिमुखाभिरेॗवैनं देव᳘ताभिरु᳘द्यछति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/01/9/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber आ ब्र᳘ह्मन्॥
ब्राह्मणो᳘ ब्रह्मवर्चसी᳘ जायतामि᳘ति ब्राह्मण᳘ एव᳘ ब्रह्मवर्चसं᳘ दधाति त᳘स्मात्पुरा᳘ ब्राह्मणो᳘ ब्रह्मवर्चसी᳘ जज्ञे॥
Eggeling [Vāj. S. XXII, 22 1], &amp;lsquo;In the priestly office (brahman) may the Brāhmaṇa be born, endowed with spiritual lustre (brahmavarcasa):&amp;rsquo; on the Brāhmaṇa he thereby bestows spiritual lustre, whence of old the Brāhmaṇa was born as one endowed with spiritual lustre 2. ०२ मूलम् - Weber आ᳘ राष्ट्रे᳘ राजन्यः᳟॥
शू᳘र इषॗव्योऽतिव्याधी᳘ महारथो᳘ जायतामि᳘ति राजन्य᳘ एव शौ᳘र्यम् महिमा᳘नं दधाति त᳘स्मात्पुरा᳘ राजन्यः᳘ शू᳘र इषॗव्योऽतिव्याधी᳘ महारथो᳘ जज्ञे॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
