<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तो वैश्वानरं᳘ जुहोति॥
अ᳘त्रैष स᳘र्वो ऽग्निः स᳘ᳫं᳘स्कृतः स᳘ एषो᳘ ऽत्र वैश्वानरो᳘ देव᳘ता त᳘स्मा एत᳘द्धवि᳘र्जुहोति त᳘देनᳫं हवि᳘षा देव᳘तां करोति य᳘स्यै वै᳘ देव᳘तायै हवि᳘र्गृह्य᳘ते सा᳘ देव᳘ता न सा य᳘स्यै न᳘ गृह्यते द्वा᳘दशकपालो द्वा᳘दश मा᳘साः संवत्सरः᳘ संवत्सरो᳘ वैश्वानरः᳟॥
Eggeling He then offers the Vaiśvānara (cake). That Agni has now been completely restored; he now is that deity, (Agni) Vaiśvānara (belonging to all men): to him he offers this oblation, and by the oblation he makes him a deity, for whatever deity an oblation is prepared that is a deity, but not one for whom no (oblation) is prepared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तो व᳘सोर्धा᳘रां जुहोति॥
अ᳘त्रैष स᳘र्वो ऽग्निः स᳘ᳫं᳘स्कृतः स᳘ एषो᳘ ऽत्र व᳘सुस्त᳘स्मै देवा᳘ एतां धा᳘राम् प्रा᳘गृह्णंस्त᳘यैनमप्रीणंस्तद्य᳘देत᳘स्मै व᳘सव एतां धा᳘राम् प्रा᳘गृह्णंस्त᳘स्मादेनां व᳘सोर्धारेत्या᳘चक्षते त᳘थैॗवास्मा अय᳘मेतां धा᳘राम् प्र᳘गृह्णाति त᳘यैनम् प्रीणाति॥
Eggeling Thereupon 1 he (the Sacrificer 2) offers the Vasor dhārā. That whole Agni has now been completed, and he is here the Vasu (good one): to that Vasu the gods offered this shower (dhārā), whence it is called &amp;lsquo;Vasor dhārā 3;&amp;rsquo; and in like manner this (Sacrificer) offers to him this shower, and gratifies him thereby.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थैता᳘न्यज्ञक्रतू᳘न्जुहोति॥
अग्नि᳘श्च मे घर्म᳘श्च म इ᳘त्येतै᳘रेॗवैनमेत᳘द्यज्ञक्रतु᳘भिः प्रीणात्य᳘थो एतै᳘रेॗवैनमेत᳘द्यज्ञक्रतु᳘भिरभि᳘षिञ्चति॥
Eggeling He then offers these Yajñakratus 1 (sacrificial rites), with,&amp;rsquo; May the Agni and the Gharma (prosper) for me!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;by these sacrificial rites he thus gratifies him, and by these sacrificial rites he thus consecrates him. ०२ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थायु᳘ज स्तो᳘मान्जुहोति॥
एतद्वै᳘ देवाः स᳘र्वान्का᳘मानाॗप्त्वायु᳘ग्भि स्तो᳘मैः स्वर्गं᳘ लोक᳘मायंस्त᳘थैॗवैतद्य᳘जमानः स᳘र्वान्का᳘माना᳘प्त्वायु᳘ग्भि स्तो᳘मैः स्वर्गं᳘ लोक᳘मेति॥
Eggeling He then offers (the libations relating to) the Uneven Stomas 2;&amp;ndash;for the gods, having now obtained their desires, by means of the uneven Stomas went up to heaven; and in like manner does the Sacrificer, now that he has obtained all his desires, by means of the uneven Stomas go up to heaven.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तो वाजप्रसवी᳘यं जुहोति॥
अ᳘न्नं वै वा᳘जो ऽन्नप्रसवी᳘यᳫं हास्यैतद᳘न्नमेॗवास्मा एते᳘न प्र᳘सौति॥
Eggeling He then offers the Vājaprasavīya 1 (set of fourteen libations),&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;vāja&amp;rsquo; (strength, sustenance) means food (anna): it thus is an &amp;lsquo;anna-prasavīya&amp;rsquo; for him, and it is food he thereby raises (pra-sū) for him (Agni). ०२ मूलम् - Weber एतद्वा᳘ एनं देवाः᳟॥
एतेना᳘न्नेन प्रीॗत्वैतैः का᳘मैरभिषि᳘च्यैत᳘या व᳘सोर्धा᳘रया᳘थैनमेतद्भू᳘य एॗवाप्रीणंस्त᳘थैॗवैनमय᳘मेत᳘देतेना᳘न्नेन प्रीॗत्वैतैः का᳘मैरभिषि᳘च्यैत᳘या व᳘सोर्धा᳘रया᳘थैनमेतद्भू᳘य एव᳘ प्रीणाति॥
Eggeling For the gods, now that they had gratified him by that food, and consecrated him by those objects of desire, (to wit) by that stream of wealth 2, hereby gratified him once more; and in like manner does this (Sacrificer), now that he has gratified him by that food, and consecrated him by those objects of desire, that shower of wealth, hereby gratify him once more.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
