<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber उपवसथीये᳘ ऽहन्प्रातरु᳘दित आदित्ये᳟॥
वा᳘चं वि᳘सृजते वा᳘चं विसृ᳘ज्य पञ्चगृहीतमा᳘ज्यं गृह्णीते त᳘त्र प᳘ञ्च हिरण्यशकलान्प्रा᳘स्यत्य᳘थैत᳘त्त्रय᳘ᳫं᳘ समा᳘सिक्तम् भवति द᳘धि म᳘धु घृत᳘म् पात्र्यां᳘ वा स्थाल्यां᳘ वोरुबिल्यां त᳘दुप᳘रिष्टाद्दर्भमुष्टिं नि᳘दधाति॥
Eggeling On the day of preparation, early in the morning, when the sun has risen, he releases his speech. Having released his speech, he takes clarified butter, in five ladlings, and throws five chips of gold thereon. Then these three (materials), sour curds, honey and ghee, are poured together, either into a dish, or a pot with a wide mouth; and he puts a handful of sacrificial grass thereon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रत्ये᳘त्याग्नि᳘म् प्रहरिष्य᳘न्॥
आ᳘हुतीश्च जुहो᳘ति समि᳘धश्चा᳘दधात्येतद्वा᳘ एनं देवा᳘ एष्य᳘न्तम् पुर᳘स्ताद᳘न्नेनाप्रीणन्ना᳘हुतिभिश्च समि᳘द्भिश्च त᳘थैॗवैनमय᳘मेत᳘देष्य᳘न्तम् पुर᳘स्ताद᳘न्नेन प्रीणात्या᳘हुतिभिश्च समि᳘द्भिश्च स वै᳘ पञ्चगृहीतं᳘ गृह्णीते त᳘स्योक्तो ब᳘न्धुः॥
Eggeling Having returned to the (Gārhapatya 1) in order to take forward the fire, he offers oblations, and puts on pieces of firewood. For now that Agni was about to go forward (to the fire-altar), the gods regaled him with food, both with oblations and pieces of firewood; and in like manner does this (Sacrificer), now that he (Agni) is about to go forward, regale him with food, both with oblations and pieces of firewood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तः सम्प्रे᳘ष्यति॥
उ᳘द्यछेध्ममु᳘पयछोपय᳘मनीरग्न᳘ये प्रह्रिय᳘माणाया᳘नुब्रूह्य᳘ग्नीदेकस्फ्य᳘यानूदे᳘हि ब्र᳘ह्मन्न᳘प्रतिरथं जपे᳘ति॥
Eggeling He (the Adhvaryu) then gives orders (to his assistant, the Pratiprasthātr̥); &amp;lsquo;Lift the log 1! hold up the underlayer!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;[To the Hotr̥], &amp;lsquo;Recite for Agni as he is taken forward!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Agnīdh, follow up with the single sword (-line)!&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Brahman, mutter the Apratiratha (hymn)!&amp;rsquo;
०२ मूलम् - Weber एतद्वै᳘ देवा᳘नुपप्रैष्य᳘तः॥
एतं᳘ यज्ञं᳘ तंस्य᳘मानान्दक्षिणतो᳘ ऽसुरा र᳘क्षांसि नाष्ट्रा᳘ अजिघांसन्न᳘ यक्ष्यध्वे न᳘ यज्ञं᳘ तंस्यध्व इ᳘ति॥
Eggeling For at that time, as the gods were about to come up in order to perform this sacrifice, the Asuras, the mischievous fiends, tried to smite them from the south, saying, &amp;lsquo;Ye shall not sacrifice!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
