<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ पर्णशाख᳘या वत्सा᳘नपा᳘करोति॥
तद्य᳘त्पर्णशाख᳘या वत्सा᳘नपाकरो᳘ति य᳘त्र वै᳘ गायत्री सो᳘ममछा᳘पतत्त᳘दस्या आह᳘रन्त्या अपाद᳘स्ताभ्याय᳘त्य पर्णम् प्र᳘चिछेद गायत्र्यै᳘ वा सो᳘मस्य वा रा᳘ज्ञस्त᳘त्पतित्वा᳘ पॗर्णो ऽभवत्त᳘स्मात्पर्णो ना᳘म तद्य᳘देवा᳘त्र सो᳘मस्य न्य᳘क्तं त᳘दिहा᳘प्यसदि᳘ति त᳘स्मात्पर्णशाख᳘या वत्सा᳘नपा᳘करोति॥
Eggeling He (the Adhvaryu) drives the calves away (from the cows) with a parṇa branch 1. The reason why he drives the calves away with a parṇa branch is this. When the Gāyatrī flew towards Soma (the moon), a footless archer aiming at her while she was carrying him off, severed one of the feathers (parṇa) either of the Gāyatrī or of king Soma 2; and on falling down it became a parṇa (palāśa) tree; whence its name parṇa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ऋण᳘ᳫं᳘ ह वै᳘ जायते यो᳘ ऽस्ति॥
स जा᳘यमान एव᳘ देवे᳘भ्य ऋ᳘षिभ्यः पितृ᳘भ्यो मनुॗष्येभ्यः॥
Eggeling Verily, whoever exists, he, in being born, is born as (owing) a debt to the gods, to the R̥shis, to the fathers, and to men 1. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स य᳘देव य᳘जेत॥
ते᳘न देवे᳘भ्य ऋणं᳘ जायते तॗद्ध्येभ्य एत᳘त्करो᳘ति य᳘देनान्य᳘जते य᳘देभ्यो जुहोति॥
Eggeling For, inasmuch as he is bound to sacrifice, for that reason he is born as (owing) a debt to the gods: hence when he sacrifices to them, when he makes offerings to them, he does this (in discharge of his debt) to them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber यज्ञे᳘न वै᳘ देवाः᳟॥
दि᳘वमुपो᳘दक्रामन्न᳘थॗ यो ऽयं᳘ देवः᳘ पशूनामीष्टे स᳘ इॗहाहीयत त᳘स्माद्वास्तव्य᳘ इ᳘त्याहुर्वा᳘स्तौ हि᳘ तद᳘हीयत॥
Eggeling Now by means of the sacrifice the gods ascended to heaven. But the god who rules over the cattle was left behind here: hence they call him Vāstavya, for he was then left behind on the (sacrificial) site 1 (vāstu).
०२ मूलम् - Weber स ये᳘नैव᳘ देवा दि᳘वमुपोद᳘क्रामन्॥
ते᳘नो एवा᳘र्चन्तः श्रा᳘म्यन्तश्चेरुर᳘थॗ यो ऽयं᳘ देवः᳘ पशूनामी᳘ष्टे य᳘ इहा᳘हीयत॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/07/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिर्ह वै स्वां᳘ दुहित᳘रमभि᳘दध्यौ॥
दि᳘वं ओष᳘सं वा मिथुॗन्येनया स्यामि᳘ति ताᳫं स᳘म्बभूव॥
Eggeling Prajāpati conceived a passion for his own daughter,&amp;ndash;either the Sky or the Dawn 1. &amp;lsquo;May I pair with her!&amp;rsquo; thus (thinking) he united with her.
०२ मूलम् - Weber तद्वै᳘ देवा᳘नामा᳘ग आस॥
य᳘ इत्थᳫं स्वां᳘ दुहित᳘रमस्मा᳘कᳫं स्व᳘सारं करोती᳘ति॥
Eggeling This, assuredly, was a sin in the eyes of the gods. &amp;lsquo;He who acts thus towards his own daughter, our sister, [commits a sin],&amp;rsquo; they thought.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
