<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०८ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०८ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थास्मै कल्याणं᳘ कुर्वन्ति 1 ॥
अ᳘थास्मै श्मशान᳘म् कुर्वन्ति॥
गृहा᳘न्वा प्रज्ञा᳘नम् वा यो वै क᳘श्च म्रि᳘यते स श᳘वस्त᳘स्मा एतद᳘न्नं करोति त᳘स्माछवान्न᳘म् श᳘वान्न᳘म् ह वै त᳘छ्मशानमित्या᳘चक्षते परो᳘क्षं श्मशा उ हैव ना᳘म पितॄणा᳘मत्ता᳘रस्ते᳘ हामु᳘ष्मिंलोके᳘ऽकृतश्मशानस्य साधुकृत्यामु᳘पदम्भयन्ति ते᳘भ्य एतद᳘न्नं करोति त᳘स्माछ्मशान्नं᳘ श्मशान्न᳘म् ह वै त᳘छ्मशानमित्या᳘चक्षते परो᳘ऽक्षम्॥
Eggeling They now 2 do what is auspicious for him. They now prepare a burial-place (śmaśāna 3) for him, (to serve him) either as a house or as a monument; for when any one dies, he is a corpse (śava), and for that (corpse) food (anna) is thereby prepared, hence &amp;lsquo;śavanna,&amp;rsquo; for, indeed, &amp;lsquo;śavanna&amp;rsquo; is what is mystically called &amp;lsquo;śmaśāna.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अन्तर्धा᳘वो है᳘के नि᳘वपन्ति॥
देवाश्चा᳘सुराश्चोभ᳘ये प्राजापत्या᳘ अस्मिं᳘लोॗकेऽस्पर्धन्त ते᳘ देवा अ᳘सुरान्त्सप᳘त्नान्भ्रा᳘तृव्यानस्मा᳘ल्लोका᳘दनुदन्त त᳘स्माद्या दै᳘व्यः प्रजा अ᳘नन्तर्हितानि ताः᳘ श्मशाना᳘नि कुर्वते᳘ऽथ या᳘ आसुर्यः᳘ प्राच्या᳘स्त्वद्ये᳘ त्वदन्त᳘र्हितानि ते᳘ चॗम्वां त्वद्य᳘स्मिंस्त्वत्॥
Eggeling Now, some bank up (the sepulchral mound) after covering up (the site). The gods and the Asuras, both of them sprung from Prajāpati, were contending for (the possession of) this (terrestrial) world. The gods drove out the Asuras, their rivals and enemies, from this world; whence those who are godly people make their sepulchres so as not to be separate (from the earth), whilst those (people) who are of the Asura nature, the Easterns and others, (make their sepulchral mounds) so as to be separated (from the earth), either on a basin 1 or on some such thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ सर्वौषध᳘म् वपति॥
य᳘देॗवादः᳘ सर्वौषधं त᳘देत᳘द्बह्वीभिस्तद्व᳘पत्ये᳘कयेदं दै᳘वं चैव तत्पि᳘त्र्यं च व्या᳘करोत्यश्वत्थे᳘ वो निष᳘दनम् पर्णे᳘ वो वसति᳘ष्कृते᳘ति ज्योग्जीवा᳘तुमेॗवैभ्य एतदा᳘शास्ते त᳘थो हैषामे᳘कैको᳘ऽपरो जर᳘सानुप्रैति॥
Eggeling He then sows (seed) of all (kinds of) herbs: what the all-herb (seed signified) on that occasion 1, that (it does) here. With many (verses 2) he sows that (former seed), with a single one this,&amp;ndash;he thus keeps the divine separate from what belongs to the Fathers,&amp;ndash;with 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/08/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थैनछङ्कु᳘भिः᳘ परिणि᳘हन्ति॥
पा᳘लाशम् पुर᳘स्ताद्ब्र᳘ह्म वै᳘ पलाशो ब्र᳘ह्मपुरोगवमेॗवैनᳫं स्वर्गं᳘ लोकं᳘ गमयति शमीम᳘यमुत्तरतः श᳘म् मेऽसदि᳘ति वारण᳘म् पश्चा᳘दघ᳘म् मे वारयाता इ᳘ति वृत्रशङ्कुं᳘ दक्षिणॗतोऽघ᳘स्यैवा᳘नत्ययाय॥
Eggeling They now fix pegs round it 1,&amp;ndash;a Palāśa (Butea frondosa) one in front,&amp;ndash;for the Palāśa is the Brahman (n.): he thus makes him go to the heavenly world with the Brahman for his leader;&amp;ndash;a Śamī (Prosopis spicigera) one on the left (north corner), in order that there may be peace (śam) for him;&amp;ndash;a Varaṇa (Crataeva Roxburghii) one behind, in order that he may ward off (vāraya) sin from him;&amp;ndash; and a Vr̥tra-peg 2 on the right (south corner) for sin not to pass beyond.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
