<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिर्ह वा᳘ इदम᳘ग्र ए᳘क एॗवास॥
स᳘ ऐक्षत कथं नु प्र᳘जायेये᳘तिॗ सो ऽश्राम्यत्स तपो ऽतप्यत स᳘ प्रजा᳘ असृजत ता अस्य प्रजाः᳘ सृष्टाः प᳘राबभूवुस्ता᳘नीमा᳘नि व᳘यांसि पु᳘रुषो वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतेर्ने᳘दिष्ठं द्विपाद्वा᳘ अयम् पु᳘रुषस्त᳘स्माद्द्विपा᳘दो व᳘यांसि॥
Eggeling Verily, in the beginning, Prajāpati alone existed here 1. He thought within himself, &amp;lsquo;How can I be propagated?&amp;rsquo; He toiled and practised austerities. He created living beings 2. The living beings created by him passed away: they are those birds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber वैश्वदेवे᳘न वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिः॥
प्रजाः᳘ ससृजे ता᳘ अस्य प्रजाः᳘ सृष्टा व᳘रुणस्य य᳘वाञ्जक्षुर्वरुॗण्यो ह वा अ᳘ग्रे य᳘वस्तद्यॗन्न्वेव व᳘रुणस्य य᳘वान्प्रा᳘दस्त᳘स्माद्वरुणप्रघासा ना᳘म॥
Eggeling Now it was by means of the Vaiśvadeva that Prajāpati produced living beings. The beings produced by him ate (ghas) Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s barley corn; for originally the barley belonged to Varuṇa. And from their eating Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s barley corn the name Varuṇapraghāsāḥ (is derived). ०२ मूलम् - Weber ता व᳘रुणो जग्राह॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber वरुणप्रघासैर्वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिः॥
प्रजा᳘ वरुणपाशात्प्रा᳘मुञ्चत्ता᳘ स्यानमीवा᳘ अकिल्विषाः᳘ प्रजाः प्रा᳘जायन्ता᳘थैतैः᳘ साकमेधै᳘रेतैर्वै᳘ देवा᳘ वृत्र᳘मघ्नन्नेतै᳘र्वेव 1 व्य᳘जयन्तॗ येय᳘मेषां वि᳘जितिस्तां त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एतैः᳘ पाप्मा᳘नं द्विष᳘न्तम् भ्रा᳘तृव्यᳫं हन्ति त᳘थो एव वि᳘जयते त᳘स्माद्वा᳘ एष᳘ एतै᳘श्चतुर्थे᳘ मासि᳘ यजते स वै᳘ द्व्यह᳘मनूचीनाहं᳘ यजते॥
Eggeling Verily, by means of the Varuṇapraghāsāḥ Prajāpati delivered the creatures from Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s noose; and those creatures of his were born without disease and blemish. Now with these Sākamedha offerings,&amp;ndash;therewith indeed the gods slew Vr̥tra, therewith they gained that supreme authority which they now wield; and so does he now therewith slay his wicked, spiteful enemy and gain the victory: this is why he performs these offerings in the fourth month (after the Varuṇapraghāsāḥ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/05/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber महाहवि᳘ष ह वै᳘ देवा᳘ वृत्रं᳘ जघ्नुः॥
ते᳘नो एव व्य᳘जयन्तॗ येय᳘मेषां वि᳘जितिस्तां त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एते᳘न पाप्मा᳘नं द्विष᳘न्तम् भ्रा᳘तृव्यᳫं हन्ति त᳘थो एव वि᳘जयते त᳘स्माद्वा᳘ एष᳘ एते᳘न यजते॥
Eggeling Verily, by means of the Great Oblation the gods slew Vr̥tra 1; by means of it they gained that supreme authority which they now wield; and so does he (the Sacrificer) thereby now slay his wicked, spiteful enemy, and gain the victory: this is why he performs this sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
