<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber समुद्रं वा᳘ऽएते प्र᳘तरन्ति ॥
ये᳘ संवत्सरा᳘य दीक्षन्ते त᳘स्य तीर्थ᳘मेव᳘ प्रायणी᳘योऽतिरा᳘त्रस्ती᳘र्थेन हि᳘ प्रस्ना᳘न्ति तद्य᳘त्प्रायणी᳘यमतिरात्र᳘मुपय᳘न्ति य᳘था तीर्थे᳘न समुद्रं᳘ प्रस्नायु᳘स्तादृक्त᳘त् ॥
Eggeling Verily, those who become initiated for (a sacrificial session of) a year cross an ocean: the Prāyaṇīya Atirātra is a flight of steps 1, for it is by means of a flight of steps that one enters (the water); and when they enter on the Prāyaṇīya Atirātra it is just as if they were entering the ocean by a flight of steps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber त᳘दाहुः ॥
क᳘स्मादुभय᳘तोज्योतिषोऽभिप्लवा भ᳘वन्त्यन्य᳘तोज्योतिः पृ᳘ष्ठ्य इ᳘तीमे वै᳘ लोका᳘ अभिप्लवा᳘ उभय᳘तोज्योतिषो वा᳘ऽइमे᳘ लोका᳘ अग्नि᳘नेत᳘ आदित्ये᳘नामु᳘त ऋत᳘वः पृ᳘ष्ठ्योऽन्य᳘तोज्योतिषो वा᳘ऽऋत᳘व एष᳘ एषां ज्यो᳘तिर्य᳘ एष त᳘पति ॥
Eggeling Here, now, they say, &amp;lsquo;Whereby are the Abhiplavas possessed of light (jyotis) on both sides 1, and the Pr̥shṭḥya of light on one side only?&amp;rsquo; Well, the Abhiplavas are these worlds, and these worlds are indeed possessed of light on both sides&amp;ndash;through the fire on this side, and through the sun on yonder side; and the Pr̥shṭḥya is the seasons, and the seasons are indeed possessed, of light on one side only: he who burns yonder (the sun) is their light.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वा᳘ऽएष᳘ संवत्सरो᳘ बृहती᳘मभिस᳘म्पन्नः ॥
द्वा᳘वार्क्ष्यताम᳘ह्नाᳫं 1 षडहौ द्वौ᳘ पृष्ठ्या᳘भिप्लवौ᳘ गोऽआयु᳘षी दशरात्रस्तत्ष᳘ट्त्रिᳫंशत्ष᳘ट्त्रिᳫंशदक्षरा वै᳘ बृहती᳘ बृहत्या वै᳘ देवाः᳘ स्वर्गे᳘ लोके᳘ऽयतन्त बृहत्या᳘ स्वर्गं᳘ लोक᳘माप्नुवंस्त᳘थोऽएॗवैष᳘ एत᳘द्बृहॗत्यैव᳘ स्वर्गे᳘ लोके य᳘तते बृहत्या᳘ स्वर्गं᳘ लोक᳘माप्नोत्य᳘थ यो᳘ बृहत्यां का᳘मस्त᳘मेॗवैते᳘नैवंविद᳘वरुन्द्धे ॥
Eggeling That year, doubtless, amounts to a Br̥hatī&amp;ndash;,there are two shaḍahas (12) of winning days 2; the two, Pr̥shṭḥya and Abhiplava (12); the Go and Āyus, and the Daśarātra (ten days)&amp;ndash;that makes thirty-six; for the Br̥hatī consists of thirty-six syllables, and by means of the Br̥hatī the gods strove to reach heaven, and by the Br̥hatī they did gain heaven; and in like manner does this one, by means of the Br̥hatī, now strive to reach heaven, and thereby gain heaven; he who knows this secures for himself whatever wish there is in the Br̥hatī.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पु᳘रुषो वै᳘ संवत्सरः᳟॥
त᳘स्य प्राण᳘ एव᳘ प्रायणी᳘योऽतिरात्रः᳘ प्राणे᳘न हि᳘ प्रय᳘न्ति वा᳘गेॗवारम्भणी᳘यम᳘हर्वा᳘चाॗ ह्यार᳘भन्ते य᳘द्यदार᳘भन्ते ॥
Eggeling The Year, indeed, is Man;&amp;ndash;the Prāyaṇīya Atirātra is his breath, for by means of the breath men go forward (prayanti); and the Ārambhaṇīya (opening) day 1 is speech, for by means of speech men undertake (ārabh) whatever they do undertake.
०२ मूलम् - Weber अय᳘मेव द᳘क्षिणो ह᳘स्तोऽभिप्लवः᳘ षडहः᳟ ॥
त᳘स्येद᳘मेव᳘ प्रथमम᳘हस्त᳘स्येद᳘मेव᳘ प्रातःसवन᳘मिदं मा᳘ध्यन्दिनᳫं स᳘वनमिदं᳘ तृतीयसवनं᳘ गायत्र्या᳘ आय᳘तने त᳘स्मादिय᳘मासाᳫं ह्र᳘सिष्ठा ॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
