<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber आत्म᳘न्नग्निं᳘ गृह्णीते चेष्य᳘न्॥
आत्म᳘नो वा᳘ एतम᳘धिजनयति यादृ᳘शाद्व जा᳘यते तादृ᳘ङ्ङेव᳘ भवति स य᳘दात्मन्न᳘गृहीत्वाग्निं᳘ चिनुया᳘न्मनु᳘ष्यादेव᳘ मनुष्यं जन᳘येन्म᳘र्त्यान्म᳘र्त्यमनपहतपाप्मनो᳘ ऽनपहतपाप्मानम᳘थ य᳘दात्म᳘न्नग्निं᳘ गृहीत्वा᳘ चिनो᳘ति त᳘दग्ने᳘रेवा᳘ध्यग्निं᳘ जन᳘यत्यमृ᳘तादमृ᳘तम᳘पहतपाप्मनो᳘ ऽपहतपाप्मानम्॥
Eggeling Being about to build Agni (the fire-altar), he takes him up into his own self; for from out of his own self he causes him to be born, and wherefrom one is born, suchlike he becomes. Now were he to build up Agni without taking him up into his own self, he would beget man from man, mortal from mortal, one not freed from sin from one not freed from sin; but when he builds up Agni after taking him up into his own self, he causes Agni to be born from Agni, the immortal from the immortal, the sinless from the sinless.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/04/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स्वयमातृणामु᳘पदधाति॥
इयं वै᳘ स्वयमातृॗणेमा᳘मेॗवैतदु᳘पदधाति ताम᳘नन्तर्हिताम् पु᳘रुषादु᳘पदधात्य᳘न्नं वै स्वयमातृॗणेयं वै स्वयमातृॗणेय᳘मु वा अ᳘न्नमस्याᳫं हि स᳘र्वम᳘न्नम् पच्यते᳘ ऽनन्तर्हितमेॗवास्मादेतद᳘न्न दधात्यु᳘त्तरामु᳘त्तरमेवास्मादेतद᳘न्नं दधाति॥
Eggeling He puts a Svayam-ātr̥ṇṇā (naturally-perforated brick) on (the gold man);&amp;ndash;the (first) naturally-perforated one being this earth, he thus puts this earth thereon. He puts it on so as not to be separate from the man; for the naturally-perforated one means food, and the naturally-perforated one means this earth, and this earth is food, since it is on her that all food ripens: he thus places food close to him (the man, Agni).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
