<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber त᳘स्य वा᳘ एत᳘स्याग्नेः᳟॥
वा᳘गेॗवोपनिष᳘द्वाचा हि᳘ चीय᳘त ऋचा य᳘जुषा साम्ने᳘ति नु दैव्या᳘थ य᳘न्मानुष्या᳘ वाचाहे᳘तीदं᳘ कुरुते᳘तीदं᳘ कुरुते᳘ति त᳘दु ह त᳘या चीयते॥
Eggeling The mystic import of this Fire-altar, doubtless, is Speech; for it is with speech that it is built: with the R̥c, the Yajus and the Sāman as the divine (speech); and when he (the Adhvaryu) speaks with human speech, &amp;lsquo;Do ye this! do ye that!&amp;rsquo; then also it (the altar) is built therewith.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘देतन्म᳘ण्डलं त᳘पति॥
त᳘न्मह᳘दुक्थं ता ।!चः स᳘ ऋचां᳘ लोको᳘ऽथ य᳘देत᳘दर्चिर्दी᳘प्यते त᳘न्महाव्रतं ता᳘नि सा᳘मानि स सा᳘म्नां लोको᳘ऽथ य᳘ एष᳘ एत᳘स्मिन्म᳘ण्डले पु᳘रुॗषः सोऽग्निस्ता᳘नि य᳘जूंषि स य᳘जुषां लोकः॥
Eggeling Now, that shining orb is the Great Litany, the R̥k-verses: this is the world of the R̥c. And that glowing light is (the hymn of) the Great Rite, the Sāman-tunes: this is the world of the Sāman. And the man in yonder orb is the Fire-altar, the Yajus-formulas: this is the world of the Yajus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber नेव वा᳘ इदमग्रे᳘ऽसदासीॗन्नेव स᳘दासीत्॥
आ᳘सीदिव वा᳘ इदम᳘ग्रेॗ नेवासीत्त᳘द्ध तन्म᳘न एॗवास॥
Eggeling Verily, in the beginning this (universe) was, as it were 1, neither non-existent nor existent; in the beginning this (universe), indeed, as it were, existed and did not exist: there was then only that Mind.
०२ मूलम् - Weber त᳘स्मादेतदृ᳘षिणाभ्य᳘नूक्तम्॥
ना᳘सदासीॗन्नो स᳘दासीत्तदा᳘नीमि᳘तिॗ नेव हि सन्म᳘नोॗ नेवा᳘सत्॥
Eggeling Wherefore it has been said by the R̥shi (R̥g-veda X, 129, 1), &amp;lsquo;There was then neither the non-existent nor the existent;&amp;rsquo; for Mind was, as it were, neither existent nor non-existent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अयं वाव᳘ लोक᳘ एॗषोऽग्नि᳘श्चितः᳟॥
तस्या᳘प एव᳘ परिश्रि᳘तो मनुॗष्या य᳘जुष्मत्य इ᳘ष्टकाः सू᳘ददोहा ओ᳘षधयश्च व᳘नस्प᳘तयश्च पु᳘रीषमा᳘हुतयः समि᳘धोऽग्नि᳘र्लोकम्पृणा तद्वा᳘ एतत्स᳘र्वमग्नि᳘मेॗवाभिस᳘म्पद्यते तत्स᳘र्वोऽग्नि᳘र्लोकम्पृणा᳘मभिस᳘म्पद्यते स यो᳘ हैत᳘देवं वे᳘द लोकम्पृणा᳘मेनम् भूत᳘मेतत्स᳘र्वमभिस᳘म्पद्यते॥
Eggeling Verily, this (brick-)built Fire-altar (Agni) is this (terrestrial) world:&amp;ndash;the waters (of the encircling ocean) are its (circle of) enclosing-stones; the men its Yajushmatīs (bricks with special formulas); the cattle its Sūdadohas 1; the plants and trees its earth-fillings (between the layers of bricks), its oblations and fire-logs 2; Agni (the terrestrial fire) its Lokampr̥ṇā (space-filling brick);&amp;ndash;thus this comes to make up the whole Agni, and the whole Agni comes to be the space-filler 3; and, verily, whosoever knows this, thus comes to be that whole (Agni) who is the space-filler 4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/05/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber कुश्रि᳘र्ह वाजश्रवॗसोऽग्निं᳘ चिक्ये॥
त᳘ᳫं᳘ होवाच सुश्रु᳘वाः कौ᳘ष्यो 1 गौ᳘तम य᳘दग्निम᳘चैषीः प्रा᳘ञ्चमेनमचैषीः प्रत्य᳘ञ्चमेनमचैषीर्न्य᳘ञ्चमेनमचैषीरुत्तान᳘मेनमचैषीः॥
Eggeling Kuśri Vājaśravasa 2 once built a fire-altar. Suśravas Kaushya then said to him, &amp;lsquo;Gautama, when thou wert just now building up Agni, didst thou build him with his face forward, or backward, or downward, or upward?&amp;rsquo; ०२ मूलम् - Weber यद्य᳘हैनम् प्रा᳘ञ्चम᳘चैषीः य᳘था प᳘राच आ᳘सीनाय पृष्ठॗतोऽन्ना᳘द्यमुपाह᳘रेत्तादृक्तन्न᳘ ते हविः प्र᳘तिग्रहीष्यति॥
Eggeling &amp;lsquo;If perchance thou hast built him looking forward, it would be just as if one were to offer food from behind to one sitting with averted face 3: he thereby will not receive thy offering.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
