<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पशुबन्धे᳘न यजते॥
पश᳘वो वै᳘ पशुबन्धः स य᳘त्पशुबन्धे᳘न य᳘जते पशुमा᳘नसानी᳘ति ते᳘न गृहे᳘षु यजेत गृहे᳘षु पशू᳘न्बध्ना इ᳘ति ते᳘न सुयवसे᳘ यजेत सुयवसे᳘ पशू᳘न्बध्ना इ᳘ति जी᳘र्यन्ति ह वै जु᳘ह्वतो य᳘जमानस्याग्न᳘योऽग्नीन्जी᳘र्यतो᳘ऽनु य᳘जमानो य᳘जमानम᳘नु गृहा᳘श्च पश᳘वश्च॥
Eggeling He performs the animal sacrifice. Now the animal sacrifice means cattle: thus, when he performs the animal sacrifice (paśubandha, the binding of the animal), it is in order that he may be possessed of cattle. Let him perform it at his home, thinking, &amp;lsquo;I will bind (attach) cattle to my home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber हविर्यज्ञ᳘विधो ह वा᳘ अन्यः᳘ पशुबन्धः᳟॥
सव᳘विधोऽन्यः स᳘ हैष᳘ हविर्यज्ञ᳘विधो य᳘स्मिन्व्रत᳘मुपन᳘यति य᳘स्मिन्नपः᳘ प्रण᳘यति य᳘स्मिन्पूर्णपात्रं᳘ निन᳘यति य᳘स्मिन्विष्णुक्रमा᳘न्क्रम᳘यत्य᳘थ हैष᳘ सव᳘विधो य᳘स्मिन्नेता᳘नि न᳘ क्रिय᳘न्ते॥
Eggeling Now there is one animal sacrifice of the Haviryajña order 1, and another of the order of the Soma-sacrifice. Of the Haviryajña order is that at which he (the Adhvaryu) brings him fast-food 2, leads water forward 3, and pours out a jarful of water 4, and at which (the Sacrificer) strides the Vishṇu-strides 5; and of the order of the Soma-sacrifice is that (animal sacrifice) at which these (rites) are not performed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स य᳘ एष᳘ बहुसारः᳟॥
स᳘ हापशव्यस्त᳘स्मात्तादृ᳘शम् पशु᳘कामो यू᳘पं न᳘ कुर्वीता᳘थ य᳘ एष᳘ फल्गु᳘प्रासहः स᳘ ह पशव्य᳘स्त᳘स्मात्तादृ᳘शम् पशु᳘कामो यूपं कुर्वीत॥
Eggeling Such a (sacrificial stake) as has much substance 1 is not auspicious to cattle, whence he who desires to have cattle should not make such a one his sacrificial stake: but such a one as is of little hardness is auspicious to cattle, whence he who desires to have cattle should make such a one his sacrificial stake.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/11/07/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स य᳘त्पशु᳘ना यक्ष्य᳘माणः॥
ए᳘कारत्निं यू᳘पं कुरुत᳘ इम᳘मेव ते᳘न लोकं᳘ जयत्य᳘थ यद्द्व्य᳘रत्निमन्तरिक्षलोक᳘मेव ते᳘न जयत्य᳘थ यत्त्र्य᳘रत्निं दि᳘वमेव ते᳘न जयत्य᳘थ यच्च᳘तुरर्त्निं दि᳘श एव ते᳘न जयति स वा᳘ एष त्र्य᳘रत्निर्वैव च᳘तुररत्निर्वा पशुबन्धयूपो᳘ भवत्य᳘थ यो᳘ऽत ऊर्ध्वः᳘ सौम्य᳘स्यैवॗ सोऽध्वर᳘स्य॥
Eggeling Now, when he who is about to perform an animal sacrifice makes a stake one cubit long, he thereby gains this (terrestrial) world; and when (he makes) one two cubits long, he thereby gains the air-world; and when be makes one three cubits long, he thereby gains the heavens; and when he makes one four cubits long, he thereby gains the regions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
