<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०६ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०६ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पु᳘रुषो ह नारायॗणोऽकामयत॥
अ᳘तितिष्ठेयᳫं स᳘र्वाणि भूता᳘न्यह᳘मेॗवेदᳫं स᳘र्वᳫं स्यामि᳘ति स᳘ एत᳘म् पुरुषमेध᳘म् पञ्चरात्र᳘म् यज्ञक्रतु᳘मपश्यत्तमा᳘हरत्ते᳘नायजत ते᳘नेष्ट्वा᳘त्यतिष्ठत्स᳘र्वाणि भूता᳘नीदᳫं स᳘र्वमभवद᳘तितिष्ठति स᳘र्वाणि भूता᳘नीदᳫं स᳘र्वम् भवति य᳘ एव᳘म् विद्वा᳘न्पुरुषमेधे᳘न य᳘जते यो᳘ वैत᳘देवम् वे᳘द॥
Eggeling Purusha Nārāyaṇa desired, &amp;lsquo;Would that I overpassed all beings! would that I alone were everything here (this universe)!&amp;rsquo; He beheld this five-days’ sacrificial performance, the Purushamedha, and took it 1, and performed offering therewith; and having performed offering therewith, he overpassed all beings, and became everything here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/06/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ य᳘स्मात्पुरुषमेधो ना᳘म॥
इमे वै᳘ लोकाः पू᳘रय᳘मेव पु᳘रुषोॗ योऽयम् प᳘वतेॗ सोऽस्या᳘म् पुरि᳘ शेते त᳘स्मात्पु᳘रुषस्त᳘स्य य᳘देषु᳘ लोकेष्व᳘न्नं त᳘दस्या᳘न्नम् मे᳘धस्तद्य᳘दस्यैतद᳘न्नम् मेधस्त᳘स्मात्पुरुषमेधो᳘ऽथो य᳘दस्मिन्मे᳘ध्यान्पु᳘रुषानाल᳘भते त᳘स्माद्वेव᳘ पुरुषमेधः॥
Eggeling And as to why it is called Purushamedha:&amp;ndash;The stronghold (pur) doubtless is these worlds, and the Purusha (spirit) is he that blows here (the wind), he bides (śī) in this stronghold (pur): hence he is the Purusha. And whatever food there is in these worlds that is its &amp;lsquo;medha,&amp;rsquo; its food; and inasmuch as this is its &amp;lsquo;medha,&amp;rsquo; its food, therefore (it is called) Purushamedha.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
