<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber रुक्म᳘म् प्रतिमु᳘च्य बिभर्ति॥
सत्य᳘ᳫं᳘ हैतद्य᳘द्रुक्भः᳘ सत्यं वा᳘ एतं य᳘न्तुमर्हति सत्ये᳘नैतं᳘ देवा᳘ अबिभरुः सत्ये᳘नैॗवैनमेत᳘द्बिभर्ति॥
Eggeling He hangs a gold plate (round his neck), and wears it; for that gold plate is the truth, and the truth is able to sustain that (fire 1): by means of the truth the gods carried it, and by means of the truth does he now carry it. ०२ मूलम् - Weber तद्यत्त᳘त्सत्य᳘म्॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber तं ति᳘ष्ठन्प्र᳘तिमुञ्चते॥
असौ वा᳘ आदित्य᳘ एष᳘ रुक्भस्ति᳘ष्ठतीव वा᳘ असा᳘वादित्यो᳘ ऽथो ति᳘ष्ठन्वै᳘ वीर्य᳘वत्तर उ᳘दङ् प्राङ् ति᳘ष्ठंस्त᳘स्योक्तो ब᳘न्धुः॥
Eggeling Standing he puts on that (gold plate) 1,&amp;ndash;for that gold plate is yonder sun, and yonder sun stands, as it were; and moreover, while standing one is stronger. [He does so] standing with his face towards north-east: the significance of this has been explained. ०२ मूलम् - Weber दृशानो रुक्भ᳘ उर्व्या व्य᳘द्यौदि᳘ति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थैनमि᳘ति प्र᳘गृह्णाति॥
एतद्वै᳘ देवा᳘ अकामयन्त पर्ज᳘न्यो रूप᳘ᳫं᳘ स्यामे᳘ति त᳘ एते᳘नात्म᳘ना पर्ज᳘न्यो रूप᳘मभवंस्त᳘थैॗवैतद्य᳘जमान एते᳘नात्म᳘ना पर्ज᳘न्यो रूप᳘म् भवति॥
Eggeling He then holds it (the fire in the pan) up thus (towards north-east). Now the gods at that time were desiring, &amp;lsquo;May we be like Parjanya (the rain-god)!&amp;rsquo; By that body (of his 1) they became like Parjanya, and in like manner does the Sacrificer by that body (of his) become like Parjanya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/06/07/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ वात्सप्रेणो᳘पतिष्ठते॥
एतद्वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिर्विष्णुक्रमैः᳘ प्रजाः᳘ सृष्ट्वा ता᳘भ्यो वात्सप्रे᳘णायुष्य᳘मकरोत्त᳘थैॗवैतद्य᳘जमानो विष्णुक्रमैः᳘ प्रजाः᳘ सृष्ट्वा ता᳘भ्यो वात्सप्रे᳘णायुष्यं᳘ करोति॥
Eggeling He then stands by him worshipping with the Vātsapra rite 1, For Prajāpati, having by means of the Vishṇu-strides produced creatures, created vital power for them by means of the Vātsapra rite; and in like manner the Sacrificer, having, by means of the Vishṇu-strides, produced creatures (or, subjects), creates vital power for them by means of the Vātsapra rite.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
