<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber भक्षयित्वा᳘ समु᳘पहूताः स्म इ᳘त्युक्त्वो᳘त्तिष्ठति॥
पुरोडाशबृगल᳘मादा᳘य तद्य᳘त्रैतदु᳘पसन्नो ऽछावाॗको ऽन्वा᳘ह त᳘दस्मै पुरोडाशबृगल᳘म् पाणा᳘वाद᳘धदाहा᳘छावाक व᳘दस्व य᳘त्ते वा᳘द्यमित्य᳘हीयत वा᳘ अछावाकः᳟॥
Eggeling Having drunk (Soma) 1 and said, &amp;lsquo;We are invited together 2,&amp;rsquo; he (the Adhvaryu) rises. He takes a piece of the cake, and at the place where the Achāvāka, being seated, is now (about to) recite, he puts the piece of cake in his hand and says, &amp;lsquo;O Achāvāka, say what thou hast to say!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber गृणा᳘ति ह वा᳘ एतद्धो᳘ता यछ᳘ᳫं᳘सति॥
त᳘स्मा एत᳘द्गृणते प्र᳘त्येॗवाध्वर्युरा᳘गृणाति त᳘स्मात्प्रतिगरो ना᳘म॥
Eggeling Now truly when the Hotr̥ praises (recites the śastra 1), he sings, and to him thus singing the Adhvaryu responds (prati-ā-gar), whence the name response (pratigara).
०२ मूलम् - Weber तं वै प्रा᳘ञ्चमासीनमा᳘ह्वयते॥
स᳘र्वे वा᳘ अन्य᳘ उद्गातुः प्रा᳘ञ्च आ᳘र्त्विज्यं कुर्वन्ति त᳘थो हास्यैतत्प्रा᳘गेवा᳘र्त्विज्यं कृत᳘म् भवति॥
Eggeling [The Hotr̥] calls upon that (Adhvaryu) seated (before him) with his face towards the east 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber इहा᳘ इहा इ᳘त्यभि᳘षुणोति॥
इ᳘न्द्रमेॗवैतदा᳘च्यावयति बृह᳘द्बृहदिती᳘न्द्रमेॗवैतदा᳘च्यावयति॥
Eggeling He presses out (the Soma juice) with &amp;lsquo;Ihā̃! Ihā̃ 1!&amp;rsquo; (hither), whereby he draws Indra nigh; and with &amp;lsquo;Br̥hat! Br̥hat!&amp;rsquo; (great), whereby he draws Indra 2 nigh.
०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ शुक्रा᳘मन्थि᳘नौ प्रथमौ᳘ गृह्णाति॥
शुक्र᳘वॗद्ध्येतत्स᳘वनम᳘थाग्रयणᳫं स᳘र्वेषुॗ ह्येष स᳘वनेषु गृह्यते᳘ ऽथ मरुत्वती᳘यम᳘थोक्थ्यमुक्था᳘नि ह्य᳘त्रा᳘पि भ᳘वन्ति॥
Eggeling The Śukra and Manthin grahas he draws first, for thereby the Soma feast comes to be supplied with pure Soma (śukra).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber घ्न᳘न्ति वा᳘ एत᳘द्यज्ञ᳘म्॥
य᳘देनं तन्व᳘ते यॗन्न्वेव रा᳘जानमभिषुण्व᳘न्ति तत्तं᳘ 1 घ्नन्ति य᳘त्पशु᳘ᳫं᳘ संज्ञप᳘यन्ति विशा᳘सति तत्तं᳘ घ्नन्त्युलूखलमुसला᳘भ्यां दृषदुपला᳘भ्याᳫं हविर्यज्ञं᳘ घ्नन्ति॥
Eggeling Now, they slay the sacrifice, when they spread (perform) it:&amp;ndash;to wit, when they press out the king (Soma), they slay him; when they quiet the victim, they slay it; and with mortar and pestle, with the upper and nether millstone, they slay the havis offering. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ एष᳘ यज्ञो᳘ हतो न᳘ ददक्षे॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/03/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber त्रया वै᳘ देवाः᳟॥
व᳘सवो रुद्रा᳘ आदित्यास्ते᳘षां वि᳘भक्तानि स᳘वनानि व᳘सूनामेव᳘ प्रातःसवनं᳘ रुद्रा᳘णाम् मा᳘ध्यन्दिनᳫं स᳘वनमादित्यानां तृतीयसवनं तद्वा अ᳘मिश्रमेव व᳘सूनाम् प्रातःसवनम᳘मिश्रं रुद्रा᳘णाम् मा᳘ध्यन्दिनᳫं स᳘वनम् मिश्र᳘मादित्या᳘नां तृतीयसवन᳘म्॥
Eggeling Now there are three kinds of gods,&amp;ndash;the Vasus, the Rudras, and the Ādityas. Between them the press-feasts are divided: the morning pressing belongs to the Vasus, the midday pressing to the Rudras, and the third pressing to the Ādityas. But the morning pressing belonged to the Vasus exclusively, and the midday pressing to the Rudras exclusively, and the third pressing to the Ādityas conjointly (with others).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
