<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘भ्रिमा᳘दत्ते॥
देव᳘स्य त्वा सवितुः᳘ प्रसॗवे ऽश्वि᳘नोर्बाहु᳘भ्याम् पूष्णो ह᳘स्ताभ्यामा᳘ददे ना᳘र्यसी᳘ति समा᳘न एत᳘स्य य᳘जुषो ब᳘न्धुर्यो᳘षो वा᳘ एषा यद᳘भ्रिस्त᳘स्मादाह ना᳘र्यसी᳘ति॥
Eggeling He takes the spade, with (Vāj. S. VI, 1), &amp;lsquo;I take thee, at the impulse of the divine Savitr̥, with the arms of the Aśvins, with the hands of Pūshan: thou art a woman.&amp;rsquo; The significance of that formula is the same (as before); and that spade (abhri, fem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber या᳘वतो वै वे᳘दिस्ता᳘वती पृथिवी᳟॥
व᳘ज्रा वै यू᳘पास्त᳘दिमा᳘मेॗवैत᳘त्पृथिवी᳘मेतैर्व᳘ज्रैः स्पृणुॗते ऽस्यै᳘ सप᳘त्नान्नि᳘र्भजति त᳘स्माद्यू᳘पैकादशिनी भवति द्वादश᳘ उपशयो᳘ भवति वि᳘तष्टस्तं᳘ दक्षिणत᳘ उपनि᳘दधाति तद्य᳘द्द्वादश᳘ उपशयो भ᳘वति॥
Eggeling Verily, as large as the altar is, so large is the earth. The sacrificial stakes are thunderbolts; and by means of these thunderbolts he obtains possession of this earth, and excludes his enemies from sharing therein. Hence there are eleven stakes, and the twelfth lies aside rough-hewn; he puts it down south (of the altar).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पशु᳘श्च वै यू᳘पश्च॥
न वा᳘ ऋते यू᳘पात्पशुमा᳘लभन्ते कदा᳘ चन तद्यत्त᳘था न᳘ ह वा᳘ एत᳘स्मा अ᳘ग्रे पश᳘वश्चक्षमिरे यद᳘न्नम᳘भिविष्यन्य᳘थेदम᳘न्नम् भूता य᳘था हैॗवायं᳘ द्विपात्पु᳘रुष उ᳘छ्रित एव᳘ᳫं᳘ हैव᳘ द्विपा᳘द उ᳘छ्रिताश्चेरुः॥
Eggeling There are both an animal and a sacrificial stake, for never do they immolate an animal without a stake. And as to why this is so:&amp;ndash;well, animals did not at first submit thereto that they should become food, as they are now become food; for just as man here walks two-footed and erect, so did they walk two-footed and erect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/07/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पा᳘शं कृत्वा प्र᳘तिमुञ्चति॥
ऋत᳘स्य त्वा देवहविः पा᳘शेन प्र᳘तिमुञ्चामी᳘ति वरुॗण्या वा᳘ एषा यद्र᳘ज्जुस्त᳘देनमेत᳘दृत᳘स्यैव पाशे प्र᳘तिमुञ्चति त᳘थो हैनमेषा᳘ वरुॗण्या र᳘ज्जुर्न᳘ हिनस्ति॥
Eggeling Having made a noose, he throws it over (the victim) with (Vāj. S. VI, 8), &amp;lsquo;With the noose of sacred order I bind thee, O oblation to the gods!&amp;rsquo; for that rope, forsooth, is Varuṇa&amp;rsquo;s: therefore he thus binds it with the noose of sacred order, and thus that rope of Varuṇa does not injure it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
