<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ प्रवराया᳘श्रावयति॥
तद्य᳘त्प्रवरा᳘याश्राव᳘यति यज्ञो वा᳘ आश्रा᳘वणं यज्ञ᳘मभिव्याहृत्या᳘थ हो᳘तारम् प्र᳘वृणा इ᳘ति त᳘स्मात्प्रवराया᳘श्रावयति॥
Eggeling He (the Adhvaryu) now utters his call for the Pravara (choosing of the Hotr̥) 1. The reason why he utters his call, is that the (Adhvaryu&amp;rsquo;s) call is the sacrifice: &amp;lsquo;having bespoke the sacrifice, I will choose the Hotr̥,&amp;rsquo; thus (he thinks, and) for this reason he utters his call for the Pravara.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अग्निर्हो᳘ता वेत्त्वग्ने᳘र्होत्रमि᳘ति अग्नि᳘रिदᳫं हो᳘ता वेत्त्वि᳘त्येॗवैत᳘दाहाग्ने᳘र्होत्रमि᳘ति त᳘स्यो हि᳘ होत्रं वे᳘त्तु प्रावित्रमि᳘ति यज्ञो वै᳘ प्रावित्रं वे᳘त्तु यज्ञमि᳘त्येॗवैत᳘दाह साधु᳘ ते यजमान देवतेति साधु᳘ ते यजमान देव᳘ता य᳘स्य ते ऽग्निर्होते᳘त्येॗवैत᳘दाह घृत᳘वतीमध्वर्यो स्रु᳘चमा᳘स्यस्वे᳘ति त᳘दध्वर्यु प्र᳘सौति स यदे᳘कामिवा᳘ह॥
Eggeling [The Hotr̥ continues], &amp;lsquo;May Agni, the priest (hotr̥), know (undertake) Agni&amp;rsquo;s priestly duty (hautram),&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;thereby he says &amp;lsquo;may Agni, as Hotr̥, know this!&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Agni&amp;rsquo;s priestly duty&amp;rsquo; he says, because it is his duty that he must know;&amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo;that means of salvation 1,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;the means of salvation, assuredly, is the sacrifice: &amp;lsquo;may he know the sacrifice&amp;rsquo; is what he thereby says.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ऋत᳘वो ह वै᳘ प्रयाजाः᳟॥
त᳘स्मात्प᳘ञ्च भवन्ति प᳘ञ्चॗ ह्यृत᳘वः॥
Eggeling The fore-offerings (prayāja), assuredly, are the seasons: hence there are five of them, for there are five seasons. ०२ मूलम् - Weber देवा᳘श्च वा अ᳘सुराश्च॥
उभ᳘ये प्राजापत्याः᳘ पस्पृधिर एत᳘स्मिन्यज्ञे᳘ प्रजा᳘पतौ पित᳘रि संवत्स᳘रे ऽस्मा᳘कमयं᳘ भविष्यत्यस्मा᳘कमय᳘म् भविष्यती᳘ति॥
Eggeling The gods and the Asuras, both of them sprang from Prajāpati, were once contending for this sacrifice, (which is) their father Prajāpati, the year: &amp;lsquo;Ours it (he) shall be!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/05/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ समि᳘धो यजति॥
प्राणा वै᳘ समि᳘धः प्राणा᳘नेॗवैतत्स᳘मिन्द्धे प्राणैर्ह्य᳘यम् पु᳘रुषः स᳘मिद्धस्त᳘स्मादभि᳘मृषे᳘ति ब्रूयाद्य᳘द्युपतापी स्यात्स य᳘द्युष्णः स्याॗदैव ता᳘वछंसेत स᳘मिद्धो हि स ता᳘वद्भ᳘वति य᳘द्यु शीतः स्यान्ना᳘शंसेत त᳘त्प्राणा᳘नेॗवास्मिन्नेत᳘द्दधाति त᳘स्मात्समि᳘धो यजति॥
Eggeling He (accordingly) pronounces the offering-prayer to the Samidhs (kindling-sticks). The Samidhs (kindlers), doubtless, are the breaths (vital airs), and he thereby kindles the breaths; for this man (the sacrificer) is kindled (animated) by his breaths: hence if he (the sacrificer) be burning (with fever, &amp;amp;c.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
