<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ स्रुवं᳘ चाज्यविला᳘पनीं चादा᳘य॥
आहवनी᳘यमभ्यै᳘ति स᳘ एता द्वा᳘दशा᳘प्तीर्जुहो᳘ति वा वाच᳘यति वा य᳘दि जुहो᳘ति य᳘दि वाच᳘यति समान᳘ एव ब᳘न्धुः॥
Eggeling Thereupon, taking the clipping-spoon (sruva) and the pot for melting butter, he goes to the Āhavanīya fire. He either offers those twelve āptis 1, or makes (the Sacrificer) pronounce (the formulas). Whether he offers, or makes him pronounce (the formulas), the significance is the same.
०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ जुहोति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber बार्हस्पत्ये᳘न चरु᳘णा प्र᳘चरति॥
तस्या᳘निष्ट एव᳘ स्विष्टकृद्भ᳘वत्य᳘थास्मा अ᳘न्नᳫं स᳘म्भरत्य᳘न्नं वा᳘ एष उ᳘ज्जयति यो᳘ वाजपे᳘येन य᳘जते ऽन्नपे᳘यᳫं ह वै ना᳘मैतद्य᳘द्वाजपे᳘यं तद्य᳘देॗवैतद᳘न्नमुद᳘जैषीत्त᳘देॗवास्मा एतत्स᳘म्भरति॥
Eggeling He now proceeds with the Bārhaspatya pap. Its svishṭakr̥t remains yet unoffered, when he (the Adhvaryu) brings 1 him (the Sacrificer) some food; for he who offers the Vājapeya wins food, vājapeya being the same as anna-peya: thus whatever food he (the Sacrificer) has thereby gained, that he (the Adhvaryu) now brings to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पूर्णाहुतिं᳘ जुहोति॥
स᳘र्वं वै᳘ पूर्णᳫं स᳘र्वम् परिगृ᳘ह्य सूया इ᳘ति त᳘स्यां व᳘रं ददाति स᳘र्वं वै व᳘रः स᳘र्वम् परिगृ᳘ह्य सूया इ᳘ति स य᳘दि काम᳘येत जुहुया᳘देतां य᳘द्यु काम᳘येता᳘पि ना᳘द्रियेत॥
Eggeling He offers a full-offering 1; for the full means the All: &amp;lsquo;May I be consecrated after encompassing the All!&amp;rsquo; thus he thinks. At this (offering) he bestows a boon; for a boon means all: &amp;lsquo;Having encompassed the All (the universe), may I be consecrated!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber वैश्वदेवे᳘न यजते॥
वैश्वदेवे᳘न वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिर्भूमा᳘नम् प्रजाः᳘ ससृजे भूमा᳘नम् प्रजाः᳘ सृष्ट्वा᳘ सूया इ᳘ति त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एत᳘द्वैश्वदेवे᳘नैव᳘ भूमा᳘नम् प्रजाः᳘ सृजते भूमा᳘नम् प्रजाः᳘ सृष्ट्वा᳘ सूया इ᳘ति॥
Eggeling He offers the Vaiśvadeva 1 (All-gods’ offering); for by means of the Vaiśvadeva, Prajāpati created abundance (of food) and creatures, thinking, &amp;lsquo;May I be consecrated, after creating abundance and creatures!&amp;rsquo; And in like manner does this (Sacrificer) now, by the Vaiśvadeva, create abundance and creatures, thinking, &amp;lsquo;May I be consecrated, after creating abundance and creatures!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/02/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber आग्नावैष्णवमे᳘कादशकपालम् पुरोडा᳘शं नि᳘र्वपति॥
ऐन्द्रावैष्णवं᳘ चरुं᳘ वैष्णवं त्रि᳘कपालं वा पुरोडाशं चरुं᳘ वा ते᳘न त्रिषंयुक्ते᳘न यजते पु᳘रुषानेत᳘द्देवा उ᳘पायंस्त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एतत्पु᳘रुषानेवो᳘पैति॥
Eggeling He prepares a cake on eleven potsherds for Agni and Vishṇu, a pap for Indra and Vishṇu, and either a cake on three potsherds, or a pap, for Vishṇu. He performs that Trishaṁyukta 1 offering. Therewith the gods came by men, and in like manner does this (king) now thereby come by men.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
