<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतेर᳘क्ष्यश्वयत्॥
तत्प᳘रापतत्ततो᳘ऽश्वः स᳘मभवद्यद᳘श्वयत्तद᳘श्वस्याश्वत्वं त᳘द्देवा᳘ अश्वमेधे᳘नैव प्र᳘त्यदधुरेष᳘ ह वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिᳫं स᳘र्वं करोतिॗ योऽश्वमेधे᳘न य᳘जते स᳘र्व एव᳘ भवति स᳘र्वस्य वा᳘ एषा प्रा᳘यश्चित्तिः स᳘र्वस्य भेषजᳫं स᳘र्वं वा᳘ एते᳘न पाप्मा᳘नं देवा᳘ अतरन्न᳘पि वा᳘ एते᳘न ब्रह्महत्या᳘मतरंस्त᳘रति स᳘र्वम् पाप्मा᳘नं त᳘रति ब्रह्महत्यांॗ योऽश्वमेधे᳘न य᳘जते॥
Eggeling Prajāpati&amp;rsquo;s eye swelled; it fell out: thence the horse was produced; and inasmuch as it swelled (aśvayat), that is the origin and nature of the horse (aśva). By means of the Aśvamedha the gods restored it to its place; and verily he who performs the Aśvamedha makes Prajāpati complete, and he (himself) becomes complete; and this, indeed, is the atonement for everything, the remedy for everything.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber परमे᳘ण वा᳘ एष स्तो᳘मेन जित्वा᳟॥
चतुष्टोमे᳘न कृतेना᳘यानामु᳘त्तरे᳘ऽहन्नेकविंशे᳘ प्रतिष्ठा᳘याम् प्र᳘तितिष्ठत्येकविंशा᳘त्प्रतिष्ठा᳘या उ᳘त्तरम᳘हरृतू᳘नन्वा᳘रोहत्यृत᳘वो वै᳘ पृष्ठा᳘न्यृत᳘वः संवत्सर᳘ ऋतु᳘ष्वेव᳘ संवत्सरे प्र᳘तितिष्ठति॥
Eggeling Now this (Sacrificer), having- conquered by means of the supreme Stoma&amp;ndash;the Katushṭoma, the Kr̥ta among dice 1,&amp;ndash;on the next day establishes himself on the Ekaviṁśa 2, as a firm foundation: from the Ekaviṁśa, as a firm foundation, he subsequently ascends to the next day, the seasons; for the Pr̥shṭḥa (-stotras) are the seasons, and the seasons are the year: it is in the seasons, in the year, he establishes himself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘त्तिॗस्रोऽनुष्टु᳘भो भ᳘वन्ति॥
त᳘स्माद᳘श्वस्त्रिभिस्ति᳘ष्ठंस्तिष्ठति यच्च᳘तस्रो गायत्र्य᳘स्तस्माद᳘श्वः स᳘र्वैः पद्भिः᳘ प्रतिद᳘धत्प᳘लायते परमं वा᳘ एतच्छ᳘न्दो य᳘दनुष्टु᳘प्परमो᳘ऽश्वः पशूना᳘म् परम᳘श्चतुष्टोम स्तो᳘मानाम् परमे᳘णैॗवैनम् परम᳘तां गमयति॥
Eggeling Inasmuch as there are three Anushṭubh verses 1 (on the first day), therefore the horse, when standing, stands on three (feet); and inasmuch as (they are made into) four Gāyatrī verses, therefore the horse, when stepping out, scampers off on all (four) feet. For that Anushṭubh, doubtless, is the highest metre, and the horse is the highest of animals; and the Katushṭoma is the highest of Stomas: by means of what is highest he thus causes him (the Sacrificer) to reach the highest position.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स᳘र्वाभ्यो वै᳘ देव᳘ताभ्यो᳘ऽश्व आ᳘लभ्यते॥
य᳘त्प्राजापत्यं᳘ कुर्याद्या᳘ देव᳘ता अ᳘पिभागास्ता᳘ भागधे᳘येन व्य᳘र्धयेछा᳘दं दद्भिर᳘वकां दन्तमूलैरित्या᳘ज्यमवदा᳘ना 1 कृत्वा᳘ प्रत्याख्या᳘यं देव᳘ताभ्य आ᳘हुतीर्जुहोति या᳘ एव᳘ देव᳘ता अ᳘पिभागास्ता᳘ भागधे᳘येन स᳘मर्धयत्यरण्येऽनू᳘च्यान्हुत्वा᳘ द्यावापृथिॗव्यामुत्तमामा᳘हुतिं जुहोति द्या᳘वापृथिव्योर्वै स᳘र्वा देव᳘ताः प्र᳘तिष्ठितास्ता᳘ एॗवैत᳘त्प्रीणाति देवासुराः सं᳘यत्ता आसन्॥
Eggeling Verily, the horse is slaughtered for all the deities: were he to make it one belonging to Prajāpati (exclusively), he would deprive the deities who are co-sharers of their share. Having made ghee (to take the part of) portions (of the horse&amp;rsquo;s body) he makes oblations 2 to the deities in mentioning them one by one with (Vāj.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स᳘र्वेषु वै᳘ लोके᳘षु॥
मृत्य᳘वोऽन्वा᳘यत्तास्ते᳘भ्यो यदा᳘हुतीर्न᳘ जुहुया᳘ल्लोके᳘-लोक एनम् मृत्यु᳘र्विन्देद्य᳘न्मृत्यु᳘भ्य आ᳘हुतीर्जुहो᳘ति लोके᳘-लोक एव᳘ मृत्युम᳘पजयति॥
Eggeling Verily, there are deaths 1 connected with all the worlds; and were he not to offer oblations to them, Death would get hold of him in every world: when he offers oblations to the Deaths 2, he wards off Death in every world.
०२ मूलम् - Weber त᳘दाहुः॥
य᳘दमु᳘ष्मै स्वा᳘हामु᳘ष्मै स्वाहे᳘ति जु᳘ह्वत्संच᳘क्षीत ब᳘हुम् मृत्यु᳘ममि᳘त्रं कुर्वीत मृत्य᳘व आत्मा᳘नम᳘पिदध्यादि᳘ति मृत्य᳘वे स्वाहेत्ये᳘कस्मा एवै᳘कामा᳘हुतिं 3 जुहोत्ये᳘को ह वा᳘ अमु᳘ष्मिंलोके᳘ मृत्यु᳘रशनाॗयैव त᳘मेॗवामु᳘ष्मिंलोके᳘ऽपजयति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/6/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘श्वस्य वा आ᳘लब्धस्य॥
मे᳘ध उ᳘दक्रामत्त᳘दश्वस्तोमी᳘यमभवद्य᳘दश्वस्तोमी᳘यं जुहोत्य᳘श्वमेव मे᳘धसा स᳘मर्धयति॥
Eggeling When the horse was slaughtered, the life-sap 1 went out of it; it became the Aśvastomīya (set of oblations 2): when he offers the Aśvastomīya (oblations) he indeed supplies the horse with life-sap. ०२ मूलम् - Weber आ᳘ज्येन जुहोति॥
मे᳘धो वा आ᳘ज्यम् मे᳘धोऽश्वस्तोमी᳘यम् मे᳘धसैॗवास्मिंस्तन्मे᳘धो दधात्या᳘ज्येन जुहोत्येतद्वै᳘ देवा᳘नाम् प्रियं धा᳘म यदा᳘ज्यम् प्रिये᳘णैॗवैनान्धा᳘म्ना स᳘मर्धयति॥
Eggeling He performs it with ghee; for ghee is life-sap, and the Aśvastomīya is life-sap: by means of life-sap he thus puts life-sap into it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/7/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber एष वै᳘ प्रभूर्ना᳘म यज्ञः᳟॥
य᳘त्रैते᳘न यज्ञे᳘न य᳘जन्ते स᳘र्वमेव प्र᳘भूतम् भवति॥
Eggeling Verily, this is the sacrifice called Strengthful: wherever they worship with this sacrifice, everything indeed becomes strong. ०२ मूलम् - Weber एष वै᳘ विभूर्ना᳘म यज्ञः᳟॥
य᳘त्रैते᳘न यज्ञे᳘न य᳘जन्ते स᳘र्वमेव वि᳘भूतम् भवति॥
Eggeling Verily, this is the sacrifice called Plenteous: wherever they worship with this sacrifice, everything indeed becomes plentiful. ०३ मूलम् - Weber एष वै व्य᳘ष्टिर्ना᳘म यज्ञः᳟॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/03/8/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तः प्रा᳘यश्चित्तीनाम्॥
यद्य᳘श्वो व᳘डवाᳫं स्क᳘न्देद्वायव्य᳘म् प᳘योऽनुनि᳘र्वपेद्वायुर्वै रे᳘तसां विकर्ता᳘ प्राणो वै᳘ वायुः᳘ प्राणो हि रे᳘तसां विकर्ता रे᳘तसैॗवास्मिंस्तद्रे᳘तो दधाति॥
Eggeling Now, then, of the expiations. If the sacrificial horse were to couple with a mare, let him in addition prepare a milk (oblation) to Vāyu;&amp;ndash;Vāyu doubtless is the transformer of seeds, for Vāyu (the wind) is the vital air, and the vital air is the transformer of seeds: by means of seed he thus puts seed into it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
