<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘द्बालाके ॥
इदं᳘ त्रिवृ᳘दे᳘ति स᳘र्वमॗन्योऽन्य᳘मभिसम्प᳘द्यमानम् ॥
कथ᳘ᳫं᳘ स्विद्यज्ञः पु᳘रुषः प्रजा᳘पतिरॗन्योऽन्यं ना᳘तिरिच्यन्तऽएते᳟ ॥
Eggeling &amp;lsquo;Seeing that all this threefold universe keeps passing into one another, O Bālāki, how is it that these,&amp;ndash;to wit, the sacrifice, Man, and Prajāpati,&amp;ndash;do not exceed one another?
०२ मूलम् - Weber य᳘दूर्ध्वा स्तो᳘मा अनुय᳘न्ति ॥
यज्ञ᳘मभ्याव᳘र्तᳫं सा᳘मभिः क᳘ल्पमानाः ॥
कथ᳘ᳫं᳘ स्वित्ते पु᳘रुषमा᳘विशन्ति कथं᳘ प्राणैः᳘ सयु᳘जो भवन्ति ॥
Eggeling Seeing that the upward Stomas follow the sacrifice, fitting themselves by repetitions with Sāmans, how do they enter man, and how do they become united with the vital airs?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पु᳘रुषो वै᳘ संवत्सरः᳟ ॥
पु᳘रुष इत्ये᳘कᳫं संवत्सर इत्ये᳘कम᳘त्र त᳘त्समं द्वे वै᳘ संवत्सर᳘स्याहोरात्रे द्वा᳘विमौ पु᳘रुषे प्राणाव᳘त्र तत्समं त्र᳘य ऋत᳘वः संवत्सर᳘स्य त्र᳘य इमे पु᳘रुषे प्राणा अ᳘त्र त᳘त्समं च᳘तुरक्षरो वै᳘ संवत्सरश्च᳘तुरक्षरोऽयं य᳘जमानो᳘ऽत्र त᳘त्समं प᳘ञ्चऽर्त᳘वः संवत्सर᳘स्य प᳘ञ्चेमे पु᳘रुषे प्राणा अ᳘त्र त᳘त्समᳫं ष᳘डृत᳘वः संवत्सर᳘स्य ष᳘डिमे पु᳘रुषे प्राणा अ᳘त्र त᳘त्सम᳘ᳫं᳘ सॗप्तऽर्त᳘वः संवत्सर᳘स्य सॗप्तेमे पु᳘रुषे प्राणा अ᳘त्र त᳘त्सम᳟म् ॥
Eggeling The Year is Man 1:&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Man&amp;rsquo; is one unit, and &amp;lsquo;year&amp;rsquo; is another, and these now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;there are in the year the two, day and night, and in man there are these two breathings, and these now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;there are three seasons in the year, and these three breathings in man, and these (two) now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;saṁvatsara (year)&amp;rsquo; consists of four syllables, and so does &amp;lsquo;yajamāna (sacrificer),&amp;rsquo; and these (two) now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;there are five seasons in the year, and these five breathings in man, and these (two) now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;there are six seasons in the year, and these six breathings in man, and these (two) now are one and the same;&amp;ndash;there are seven seasons in the year, and these seven breathings in man, and these (two) now are one and the same.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber देवा᳘ ह वै᳘ सह᳘स्रसंवत्सराय दिदीक्षिरे 1 ॥
ते᳘षां प᳘ञ्च शता᳘नि संवत्सरा᳘णां पर्य᳘वेतान्यासुर᳘थेदᳫं स᳘र्वमेव᳘ शश्राम ये स्तो᳘मा या᳘नि पृष्ठा᳘नि या᳘नि छ᳘न्दाᳫंसि ॥
Eggeling The gods were once performing the initiation ceremony for a (sacrificial session) of a thousand years. When five hundred years had passed with them, everything here was worn out&amp;ndash;to wit, Stomas, and Pr̥shṭḥas, and metres (texts). ०२ मूलम् - Weber त᳘तो देवाः᳘ ॥
एत᳘द्यज्ञस्या᳘यातयामापश्यंस्तेना᳘यातयाम्ना 2 या वे᳘देॗ व्यष्टिरा᳘सीत्तां ॗ व्याश्नुवता᳘यातयामा वा᳘ऽअस्य वे᳘दा अ᳘यातयाम्न्या हास्य त्रय्या᳘ विद्यया᳘र्त्विज्यं कृतं᳘ भवति य᳘ एव᳘मेतद्वे᳘द ॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पु᳘रुषᳫं ह नारायणं᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिरुवाच ॥
य᳘जस्व-यजस्वे᳘ति स᳘ होवाच य᳘जस्व-यजस्वे᳘ति वाव त्वं मा᳘मात्थ त्रि᳘रयक्षि व᳘सवः प्रातःसवने᳘नागू रुद्राः मा᳘ध्यन्दिनेन स᳘वनेनादित्या᳘स्तृतीयसवनेना᳘थ म᳘म यज्ञवाॗस्त्वेव᳘ यज्ञवास्ता᳘वेॗवाह᳘मासऽइ᳘ति ॥
Eggeling Prajāpati once upon a time spake unto Purusha Nārāyaṇa, &amp;lsquo;Offer sacrifice! offer sacrifice!&amp;rsquo; He spake, &amp;lsquo;Verily, thou sayest to me, &amp;ldquo;Offer sacrifice! offer sacrifice!&amp;rdquo; and thrice have I offered sacrifice: by the morning-service the Vasus went forth, by the midday-service the Rudras, and by the evening-service the Ādityas; now I have but the offering-place 1, and on the offering-place I am sitting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/12/03/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber सावित्र᳘ᳫं᳘ ह स्मैतं पू᳘र्वे पशुमा᳘लभन्ते ॥
अ᳘थैत᳘र्हि प्राजापत्यं योॗ ह्येव᳘ सविता स᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिरि᳘ति व᳘दन्तस्त᳘स्मात्संन्यु᳘प्याग्नींस्ते᳘न यजेरन्गृह᳘पतेरेॗवाग्नि᳘षु य᳘येदं जा᳘घन्या प᳘त्नीः संयाज᳘यन्ति त᳘स्यां नो᳘ऽप्यसदि᳘ति ते त᳘तो यदानिका᳘मं दी᳘क्षन्ते ॥
Eggeling Of old, indeed, they were wont to seize this victim as one dedicated to Savitr̥, but now they seize it as one dedicated to Prajāpati, saying, &amp;lsquo;Savitr̥, in truth, is the same as Prajāpati.&amp;rsquo; It is therefore after having thrown together the (sacrificial) fires that they ought to perform this (animal) sacrifice on the Gr̥hapati&amp;rsquo;s own fires, thinking, &amp;lsquo;May we also have a share in this tail (of the.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
