<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber हिंकृत्या᳘न्वाह॥
नासामा᳘ यॗज्ञो ऽस्ती᳘ति वा᳘ आहुर्न वा अ᳘हिंकृत्य सा᳘म गीयते म य᳘द्धिंकरो᳘ति त᳘द्धिंकार᳘स्य रूपं᳘ क्रियते प्रणवे᳘नैव सा᳘म्नो रूपमु᳘पगछत्यो३ं ओ३मि᳘त्येते᳘नो हास्यैष स᳘र्व एव स᳘सामा यज्ञो᳘ भवति॥
Eggeling He recites after uttering (the syllable) &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ!&amp;rsquo; Sacrifice, they say, is not (performed) without the Sāman; and neither is the Sāman chanted without &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ&amp;rsquo; having been uttered. By his uttering &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ!&amp;rsquo; the peculiar nature (rūpam) of the word &amp;lsquo;Hiṅ&amp;rsquo; is produced (in the sacrifice); and by the sacred syllable (om) it assumes the nature of the Sāman.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber एत᳘द्ध वै᳘ देवा᳘ अग्निं ग᳘रिष्ठे ऽयुञ्जन्॥
य᳘द्धोतृत्व᳘ इदं᳘ नो हव्यं᳘ वहे᳘ति त᳘मेतद्ग᳘रिष्ठे युक्त्वो᳘पामदन्वीर्य᳘वान्वै त्व᳘मस्य᳘लं वै त्व᳘मेत᳘स्मा असी᳘ति वीॗर्ये समाद᳘धतो य᳘थेदम᳘ष्येत᳘र्हि ज्ञातीनां यं ग᳘रिष्ठे युञ्ज᳘न्ति त᳘मुपम᳘दन्ति वीर्य᳘वान्वै त्व᳘मस्य᳘लं वै त्व᳘मेत᳘स्मा असी᳘ति वीॗर्ये समाद᳘धतः स यद᳘मेॗवास्मिन्दधाति॥
Eggeling Now in former times the gods appointed Agni to the chief (office), namely, that of Hotr̥; and having appointed him to the chief (office) saying &amp;lsquo;do thou carry this our oblation!&amp;rsquo; they cheered him up, saying, &amp;lsquo;Surely, thou art vigorous; surely, thou art equal to this!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber यो᳘ ह वा᳘ अग्निः᳘ सामिधेनी᳘भिः स᳘मिद्धः॥
अतितरा᳘ᳫं᳘ ह वै स इ᳘तरस्मादग्ने᳘स्तपत्यनवधृष्यो हि भ᳘वत्यनवमृश्यः॥
Eggeling The fire that has been kindled by means of the kindling verses, assuredly, blazes more brightly than any other fire; for, indeed, it is unassailable, unapproachable. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स य᳘था हैॗवाग्निः᳟॥
सामिधेनी᳘भिः स᳘मिद्धस्त᳘पत्येव᳘ᳫं᳘ हैव᳘ ब्राह्मणः᳘ सामिधेनी᳘र्विद्वा᳘ननुब्रुवंस्तपत्यनवधृष्यो हि भ᳘वत्यनवमृश्यः॥
Eggeling And in like manner as the fire blazes when kindled by means of the kindling verses, so also blazes the priest (brāhmaṇa) that knows and recites the kindling verses; for, indeed, he is unassailable, unapproachable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber तं वा᳘ एत᳘मग्निᳫं स᳘मैन्धिषत॥
स᳘मिद्धे देवे᳘भ्यो जुहवामे᳘ति त᳘स्मिन्नेते᳘ एव᳘ प्रथमे आ᳘हुती जुहोती म᳘नसे चैव᳘ वाचे᳘ च म᳘नश्च हैव वा᳘क्च यु᳘जौ देवे᳘भ्यो यज्ञं᳘ वहतः॥
Eggeling That same fire, then, they have kindled, (thinking), &amp;lsquo;In it, when kindled, we will sacrifice to the gods.&amp;rsquo; In it, indeed, he makes these two first oblations 1 to Mind and Speech (or, Voice); for mind and speech, when yoked together, convey the sacrifice to the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/01/04/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ स्रुचो᳘त्तरमाघार᳘माघारयिष्य᳘न्॥
पू᳘र्वेण स्रु᳘चावञ्जलिं नि᳘दधाति न᳘मो देवे᳘भ्यः स्वधा᳘ पितृ᳘भ्य इ᳘ति त᳘द्देवे᳘भ्यश्चैॗवैत᳘त्पितृ᳘भ्यश्चा᳘र्त्विज्यं करिष्यन्नि᳘ह्नुते सुय᳘मे मे भूयास्तमि᳘ति स्रु᳘चावा᳘दत्ते सुभ᳘रे मे भुयास्तम् भ᳘र्तुं वां शकेयमि᳘त्येॗवैत᳘दाहा᳘स्कन्नमद्य᳘ देवे᳘भ्य आ᳘ज्यᳫं स᳘म्भ्रियासमित्य᳘विक्षुब्धमद्य᳘ देवे᳘भ्यो यज्ञं᳘ तनवा इ᳘त्येॗवैत᳘दाह॥
Eggeling When he (the Adhvaryu) is about to make the second libation with the offering-spoon (sruc), he (twice) lays his joined hands (añjali) on the ground before the two offering-spoons (juhū and upabhr̥t), with the formulas (Vāj. S.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
