<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber उद्धृ᳘त्याहवनी᳘यम् पूर्णाहुतिं᳘ जुहोति॥
तद्य᳘त्पूर्णाहुतिं᳘ जुहो᳘त्यन्नादं वा᳘ एत᳘मात्म᳘नो जन᳘यते य᳘दग्निं 1 त᳘स्मा एत᳘दन्ना᳘द्यम᳘पिदधाति य᳘था कुमारा᳘य वा जाता᳘य वत्सा᳘य वा स्त᳘नमपिदध्या᳘देव᳘मस्मा एत᳘दन्ना᳘द्यम᳘पिदधाति॥
Eggeling When he has taken out the Āhavanīya fire 2, he performs the Full-offering 3. The reason why he performs the full-offering is that he thereby causes that Agni to become an eater of food for his own self; that he thereby offers food to him. Even as (a mother or cow) would offer the breast to a new-born child or calf, so does he thereby offer food to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber घ्न᳘न्ति वा एत᳘द्यज्ञम्॥
य᳘देनं तन्व᳘ते यन्न्वे᳘व 1 रा᳘जानमभिषुण्व᳘न्ति तत्तं᳘ घ्नन्ति य᳘त्पशु᳘ᳫं᳘ सम्ज्ञप᳘यन्ति विशा᳘सति तत्तं᳘ घ्नन्त्युलूखलमुसला᳘भ्यां दृषदुपला᳘भ्याᳫं हविर्यज्ञं᳘ घ्नन्ति॥
Eggeling Now, in performing that sacrifice, they slay it; and in pressing out the king (Soma), they slay him; and in quieting and immolating the victim, they slay it. The haviryajña they slay with the mortar and pestle, and with the two mill-stones. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ एष᳘ यज्ञो᳘ हतो न᳘ ददक्षे॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber व᳘रुणो हैनद्राज्य᳘काम आ᳘दधे॥
स राज्य᳘मगछत्त᳘स्माद्य᳘श्च वे᳘द य᳘श्च न व᳘रुणो राजे᳘त्येॗवाहुः सो᳘मो य᳘शस्कामः स य᳘शो ऽभवत्त᳘स्माद्य᳘श्च सो᳘मे ल᳘भते य᳘श्चॗ नोभा᳘वेवा᳘गछतो य᳘श एॗवैतद्द्र᳘ष्टुमा᳘गछन्ति य᳘शो ह भवति राज्यं᳘ गछति य᳘ एवं᳘ विद्वा᳘नाधत्ते॥
Eggeling Now Varuṇa established this (fire), being desirous of sovereignty. He obtained sovereignty; and, accordingly, whether one (who has established the fires) knows (this) or not, they call him &amp;lsquo;king Varuṇa.&amp;rsquo; Soma (established the fire), being desirous of glory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिर्ह वा᳘ इदम᳘ग्र ए᳘क एॗवास॥
स᳘ ऐक्षत कथं नु प्र᳘जायेये᳘ति सो ऽश्राम्यत्स त᳘पो ऽतप्यतॗ सो ऽग्नि᳘मेव मु᳘खाज्जनयां᳘ चक्रे तद्य᳘देनम् मु᳘खाद᳘जनयत त᳘स्मादन्नाॗदो ऽग्निः स यो᳘ हैव᳘मेत᳘मग्नि᳘मन्नादं वे᳘दान्नादो᳘ हैव भ᳘वति॥
Eggeling Prajāpati alone, indeed, existed here in the beginning. He considered, &amp;lsquo;How may I be reproduced?&amp;rsquo; He toiled and performed acts of penance. He generated Agni from his mouth; and because he generated him from his mouth, therefore Agni is a consumer of food: and, verily, he who thus knows Agni to be a consumer of food, becomes himself a consumer of food.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
