<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तो राष्ट्रभृ᳘तो जुहोति॥
रा᳘जानो वै᳘ राष्ट्रभृ᳘तस्ते हि᳘ राष्ट्रा᳘णि बि᳘भ्रत्येता᳘ ह देव᳘ताः सुता᳘ एते᳘न सवे᳘न ये᳘नैत᳘त्सोष्य᳘माणो भ᳘वति ता᳘ एॗवैत᳘त्प्रीणाति ता᳘ अस्मा इष्टाः᳘ प्रीता᳘ एत᳘ᳫं᳘ सवम᳘नुमन्यन्ते ता᳘भिर᳘नुमतः सूयते य᳘स्मै वै रा᳘जानो राज्य᳘मनुम᳘न्यन्ते स रा᳘जा भवति न स य᳘स्मै न तद्यद्रा᳘जानो राष्ट्रा᳘णि बि᳘भ्रति रा᳘जान उ एते᳘ देवास्त᳘स्मादेता᳘ राष्ट्रभृतः॥
Eggeling He then offers the Rāshṭrabhr̥t (realm-sustaining) oblations;&amp;ndash;the realm-sustainers, doubtless, are the kings, for it is they that sustain realms. These deities, indeed, have been consecrated by this same consecration ceremony by which he (the Sacrificer) is now to be consecrated: it is them he thereby gratifies, and thus gratified by offering, they grant him permission (to perform) this consecration ceremony, and, permitted by them, he is consecrated; for only he becomes king whom the (other) kings allow (to assume) the royal dignity, but not he whom they do not (allow to assume it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ वातहोमा᳘न्जुहोति॥
इमे वै᳘ लोका᳘ एॗषो ऽग्नि᳘र्वायु᳘र्वातहोमा᳘ एषु त᳘ल्लोके᳘षु वायुं᳘ दधाति त᳘स्मादय᳘मेषु᳘ लोके᳘षु वायुः᳟॥
Eggeling He then offers (three) oblations of air;&amp;ndash;this fire-altar is these (three) worlds, and the oblations of air are wind: he thus places the wind into these worlds, and hence there is wind here in these worlds. ०२ मूलम् - Weber बा᳘ह्येनाग्निमा᳘हरति॥
आप्तो वा᳘ अस्य स᳘ वायुर्य᳘ एषु᳘ लोकेष्व᳘थ य᳘ इमां᳘लोकान्प᳘रेण वायुस्त᳘मस्मिन्नेत᳘द्दधाति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ प्रत्ये᳘त्य धि᳘ष्ण्यानां काले धि᳘ष्ण्यान्नि᳘वपति॥
अग्न᳘य एते यद्धि᳘ष्ण्या अग्नी᳘नेॗवैत᳘च्चिनोति ता᳘ एता वि᳘शः क्षत्र᳘मय᳘मग्नि᳘श्चितः᳘ क्षत्रं᳘ च तद्वि᳘शं च करोत्यमुम् पू᳘र्वं चिनोत्य᳘थेमा᳘न्क्षत्रं त᳘त्कृत्वा वि᳘शं करोति॥
Eggeling Having now returned (to the hall), he, at the proper time, throws up the Dhishṇyas 1 (fire-hearths)&amp;ndash;these hearths are fires: he thus builds up fire-altars. They are the clansmen, and the built-up fire-altar is the chieftaincy: he thus sets up both the chieftaincy and the clan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/09/04/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ प्रातः᳘ प्रातरनुवाक᳘मुपाकरिष्य᳘न्॥
अग्निं᳘ युनक्ति युक्ते᳘न स᳘मश्नवा इ᳘ति ते᳘न युक्ते᳘न स᳘र्वान्का᳘मान्त्स᳘मश्नुते तं वै᳘ पुर᳘स्तात्स᳘र्वस्य क᳘र्मणो युनक्ति तद्यत्किं चा᳘त्र ऊर्ध्वं᳘ क्रिय᳘ते युक्ते तत्स᳘र्वᳫं समा᳘धीयते॥
Eggeling Then, early next morning 1, when about to bespeak the morning prayer 2, he yokes the Fire-altar, thinking, &amp;lsquo;With it, when yoked, I shall obtain; and by it, when yoked, he obtains all wishes. He yokes it prior to the whole performance, so that all that is done thereafter is laden on that yoked (altar-cart).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
