<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber गा᳘र्हपत्यं चेष्य᳘न्पलाशशाख᳘या व्यु᳘दूहति॥
अ᳘वस्यति हैतद्यद्गा᳘र्हपत्यं चिनो᳘ति य᳘ उ वै के᳘ चाग्निचि᳘तो ऽस्या᳘मेव ते᳘ ऽवसितास्तद्य᳘द्व्युदू᳘हत्य᳘वसितानेव तद्व्यु᳘दूहति नेद᳘वसितानध्यवस्यानी᳘ति॥
Eggeling Being about to build the Gārhapatya (fire-place), he sweeps (its site) with a Palāśa (butea frondosa) branch. For when he builds the Gārhapatya 1 he settles on that place; and whatsoever builders of fire-altars (there have been), they are indeed settled on this earth; and when he sweeps (that place) he thereby sweeps away those settled (there before hire), thinking, &amp;lsquo;Lest I should settle on those already settled (here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/07/01/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिः प्रजा᳘ असृजत॥
स᳘ प्रजाः᳘ सृष्ट्वा स᳘र्वमाजि᳘मित्वा व्य᳘स्रंसत त᳘स्माद्वि᳘स्रस्तात्प्राणो᳘ मध्यत उ᳘दक्रामद᳘थास्माद्वीर्य᳘मु᳘दक्रामत्त᳘स्मिन्नु᳘त्क्रान्ते ऽपद्यत त᳘स्मात्पन्नाद᳘न्नमस्रवद्यच्च᳘क्षुरध्य᳘शेत त᳘स्मादस्या᳘न्नमस्रवन्नो हेह त᳘र्हि का चन᳘ प्रतिॗष्ठास॥
Eggeling Prajāpati produced creatures. Having produced creatures, and run the whole race, he became relaxed 1. From him, when relaxed, the vital air went out from within: then his vigour went out of him. That having gone out, he fell down. From him, thus fallen, food flowed forth: it was from that eye on which he lay that his food flowed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
