<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०५ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber आग्नेॗयो ऽष्टा᳘कपालः पुरोडा᳘शो भवति॥
त᳘म् पूर्वार्ध आ᳘सादयत्यैन्द्र ए᳘कादशकपालः पुरोडा᳘शो भवति सौम्यो᳘ वा चरुस्तं᳘ दक्षिणार्ध आ᳘सादयति वैश्वदेव᳘श्चरु᳘र्भवति त᳘म् पश्चार्ध आ᳘सादयति मैत्रावरुणी᳘ पयॗस्या भवति ता᳘मुत्तरार्ध आ᳘सादयति बार्हस्पत्य᳘श्चरु᳘र्भवति तम् म᳘ध्य आ᳘सादयत्येष᳘ चरुः प᳘ञ्चबिलस्तद्यत्प᳘ञ्च हवीं᳘षि भ᳘वन्ति ते᳘षाम् प᳘ञ्च बि᳘लानि त᳘स्माच्चरुः प᳘ञ्चबिलो ना᳘म॥
Eggeling There is a cake on eight potsherds for Agni: this he places on the eastern part (of the Vedi). There is either a cake on eleven potsherds for Indra, or a rice-pap for Soma: this he places on the southern part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ प्रयु᳘जाᳫं हवि᳘र्भिर्यजते॥
तद्य᳘त्प्रयु᳘जाᳫं हवि᳘र्भिर्य᳘जत ऋतून्वा᳘ एत᳘त्सुषुवाणो᳘ युङ्क्ते त᳘ एनमृत᳘वो युक्ता᳘ वहन्त्यृतू᳘न्वा प्र᳘युक्तान᳘नुचरति त᳘स्मात्प्रयु᳘जाᳫं हवि᳘र्भिर्यजते॥
Eggeling He performs the oblations of teams (prayujāṁ havīṁshi). The reason why he performs the oblations of teams, is that the anointed thereby yokes the seasons, and thus yoked those seasons draw him along, and he follows the seasons thus yoked: therefore he performs the oblations of teams. ०२ मूलम् - Weber ता᳘नि वै द्वा᳘दश भवन्ति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अभिषेचनी᳘येनेष्ट्वा᳟॥
के᳘शान्न᳘ वपते तद्यत्के᳘शान्न व᳘पते वीर्यं᳘ वा᳘ एत᳘दपां र᳘सः स᳘म्भृतो भवति ये᳘नैनमेत᳘दभिषिञ्च᳘ति त᳘स्याभि᳘षिक्तस्य के᳘शान्प्रथमान्प्रा᳘प्नोति स यत्के᳘शान्व᳘पेतैतां श्रि᳘यम् जिह्मां वि᳘नाशयेद्व्युदुह्यात्त᳘स्मात्के᳘शान्न᳘ 1 वपते॥
Eggeling When he has performed the Consecration-ceremony (Abhishecanīya), he does not shave his hair. The reason why he does not shave his hair (is this):&amp;ndash;that collected essence of the waters wherewith he is then sprinkled (anointed) is vigour, and it is the hair (of his head) that it reaches first when he is sprinkled; hence were he to shave his hair, he would cause that glory to fall off from him, and would sweep it away: therefore he does not shave his hair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber श्ये᳘त आश्विनो᳘ भवति॥
श्ये᳘ताविव ह्य᳘श्वि᳘नाव᳘विर्मल्हा᳘ सारस्वती᳘ भवत्यृषभमि᳘न्द्राय सृत्रा᳘म्ण आ᳘लभते दुर्वे᳘दा एव᳘ᳫं᳘समृद्धाः पश᳘वो य᳘द्येव᳘ᳫं᳘समृद्धान्न᳘ विन्देद᳘प्यजा᳘नेवा᳘लभेरंस्ते हि᳘ सुश्र᳘पतरा 1 भ᳘वन्ति स य᳘द्यजा᳘नाल᳘भेरंलो᳘हित आश्विनो᳘ भवति तद्य᳘देत᳘या य᳘जते॥
Eggeling There is a reddish-white (he-goat as the victim) for the Aśvins 2, for the Aśvins are reddish-white. There is an ewe with teats in the dewlap 3 for Sarasvatī; and a bull he seizes for Indra Sutrāman (the good protector) 4. Difficult to obtain are beasts with such perfections; if he cannot obtain any with such perfections, they may slaughter only goats, for they are easier to cook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/05/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ऐन्द्रवैष्णवं द्वा᳘दशकपालम् पुरोडा᳘शं नि᳘र्वपति॥
तद्य᳘देत᳘या य᳘जते वृत्रे᳘ ह वा᳘ इदम᳘ग्रे स᳘र्वनाम यदृ᳘चो यद्य᳘जूंषि यत्सा᳘मानि त᳘स्मा इ᳘न्द्रो व᳘ज्रम् प्रा᳘जिहीर्षत्॥
Eggeling He prepares a cake on twelve potsherds for Indra and Vishṇu. Now as to why he makes this offering. Of old, everything here was within Vr̥tra, to wit, the R̥c, the Yajus, and the Sāman. Indra wished to hurl the thunderbolt at him. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘ ह वि᳘ष्णुमुवाच॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
