<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber द᳘क्षिणेनाहवनी᳘यम् प्राची᳘नग्रीवे कृष्णाजिने उ᳘पस्तृणाति॥
त᳘योरेनम᳘धि दीक्षयति य᳘दि द्वे भ᳘वतस्तदन᳘योर्लोक᳘यो रूपं त᳘देनमन᳘योर्लोक᳘योर᳘धि दीक्षयति॥
Eggeling South of the Āhavanīya he spreads two black antelope skins on the ground, with the neck parts towards the east: thereon he consecrates him. If there are two (skins), they are an image of these two worlds (heaven and earth), and thus he consecrates him on these two worlds. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स᳘म्बद्धान्ते भवतः॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber वा᳘चं यछति॥
स᳘ वाचंयम᳘ आस्तॗ आस्तमयात्तद्यद्वा᳘चं यछति॥
Eggeling He maintains silence; and silently he remains seated till sunset. The reason why he maintains silence is this: ०२ मूलम् - Weber यज्ञे᳘न वै᳘ देवाः᳟॥
इमां जि᳘तिं जिग्युॗर्यैषामियं जि᳘तिस्ते होचुः कथं᳘ न इद᳘म् मनुॗष्यैरनभ्यारोह्य᳘ᳫं᳘ स्यादि᳘ति ते᳘ यज्ञ᳘स्य रसं धीत्वा य᳘था म᳘धु मधुकृ᳘तो निर्ध᳘येयुर्विदु᳘ह्य यज्ञं यू᳘पेन योपयित्वा᳘ तिॗरो ऽभवन्न᳘थ य᳘देनेना᳘योपयंस्त᳘स्माद्यू᳘पो ना᳘म॥
Eggeling By means of the sacrifice the gods gained that supreme authority which they now wield.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber आदित्यं᳘ चरु᳘म् प्रायणी᳘यं नि᳘र्वपति॥
देवा᳘ ह वा᳘ अस्यां᳘ यज्ञं᳘ तन्वाना᳘ इमां᳘ यज्ञा᳘दन्त᳘रीयुः सा᳘ हैषामियं᳘ यज्ञ᳘म् मोहयां᳘ चकार कथं नु म᳘यि यज्ञं᳘ तन्वाना मां᳘ यज्ञा᳘दन्त᳘रीयुरि᳘ति तᳫं ह यज्ञं न प्र᳘जज्ञुः॥
Eggeling He prepares the Prāyaṇīya rice-pap for Aditi. Now while the gods were spreading (performing) the sacrifice on this (earth) they excluded her (the earth) from the sacrifice. She thought, &amp;lsquo;How is it that, in spreading the sacrifice on me, they should exclude me from the sacrifice?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/03/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber दिवि वै सो᳘म आ᳘सीत्॥
अ᳘थेह᳘ देवास्ते᳘ देवा᳘ अकामयन्ता᳘ नः सो᳘मो गछेत्तेना᳘गतेन यजेमही᳘ति त᳘ एते᳘ माये᳘ असृजन्त सुपर्णीं᳘ च कद्रूं᳘ च तद्धि᳘ष्ण्यानाम् ब्रा᳘ह्मणे व्या᳘ख्यायते सौ᳘पर्णीकाद्रवं य᳘था तदा᳘स॥
Eggeling Now Soma was in the sky, and the gods were here on earth. The gods desired,&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;Would that Soma came to us: we might sacrifice with him, when come.&amp;rsquo; They created those two illusions, Suparṇī and Kadrū. In the chapter on the hearths (dhishṇya 1) it is set forth how that affair of Suparṇī and Kadrū came to pass.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
