<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०६ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०६ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber नाकस᳘द उ᳘पदधाति॥
देवा वै᳘ नाकसदो᳘ ऽत्रैष स᳘र्वो ऽग्निः स᳘ᳫं᳘स्कृतः स᳘ एषो᳘ ऽत्र ना᳘कः स्वर्गो᳘ लोकस्त᳘स्मिन्देवा᳘ असीदंस्तद्य᳘देत᳘स्मिन्ना᳘के स्वर्गे᳘ लोके᳘ देवा अ᳘सीदंस्त᳘स्माद्देवा᳘ नाकस᳘दस्त᳘थैॗवैतद्य᳘जमानो य᳘देता᳘ उपद᳘धात्येत᳘स्मिन्नेॗवैतन्ना᳘के स्वर्गे᳘ लोके᳘ सीदति॥
Eggeling He lays down the Nākasads (firmament-seated bricks): the firmament-seated ones, assuredly, are the gods. In this (layer) that whole fire-altar becomes completed, and therein these (bricks are) the firmament (nāka), the world of heaven: it is therein that the gods seated themselves; and inasmuch as the gods seated themselves on that firmament, in the world of heaven, the gods are the firmament-seated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber छन्दॗस्या उ᳘पदधाति॥
अ᳘त्रैष स᳘र्वो ऽग्निः स᳘ᳫं᳘स्कृतः स᳘ एषो᳘ ऽत्र श्रि᳘यमैछॗन्नो हैषो᳘ ऽतः पुरा त᳘स्मा अ᳘लमास यछ्रि᳘यम᳘धारयिष्यत्त᳘स्मादिदम᳘प्येत᳘र्ह्याहुर्न वा᳘ एषो᳘ ऽलं श्रियै धा᳘रणाय राज्या᳘य वा ग्रा᳘मणीथ्याय वे᳘ति त᳘स्मै देवा᳘ एतां श्रि᳘यम् प्रा᳘यछन्नेता᳘श्छन्दॗस्याः पश᳘वो छ᳘न्दांस्य᳘न्नम् पशवो᳘ ऽन्नमु श्रीः᳟॥
Eggeling He lays down Chandasyās 1 (bricks pertaining to the metres). Completed now was the entire Agni (fire-altar). He now wished for distinction 2; for, indeed, heretofore he was not equal thereto, that he should sustain distinction; whence people here say even to this day, &amp;lsquo;This one is not equal to sustain distinction, either in regard to kingship or to headmanship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/06/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber गा᳘र्हपत्यमु᳘पदधाति॥
एतद्वै᳘ देवाः प्रा᳘प्य राॗद्ध्वेवामन्यन्त᳘ 1 ते ऽब्रुवन्के᳘नेद᳘मरात्स्मे᳘ति गा᳘र्हपत्येनैवे᳘त्यव्रुवन्गा᳘र्हपत्यं वै᳘ चित्वा᳘ समारु᳘ह्य प्रथमां चि᳘तिमपश्याम प्रथमा᳘यै द्विती᳘यां द्विती᳘यायै तृती᳘यां तृती᳘यायै चतुर्थीं᳘ चतुर्थ्यै᳘ पञ्चमी᳘म् पञ्चम्या᳘ इद᳘मिति॥
Eggeling He lays down the Gārhapatya. For the gods, having obtained this much, thought they had succeeded. They spake, &amp;lsquo;Whereby have we succeeded in this?&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;By means of the Gārhapatya,&amp;rsquo; they said; &amp;lsquo;for, after building the Gārhapatya 2 and mounting thereon, we saw the first layer, from the first (we saw) the second, from the second the third, from the third the fourth, from the fourth the fifth, and from the fifth this one.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
