<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber सू᳘र्यो ह वा᳘ अग्निहोत्रम्॥
तद्य᳘देत᳘स्या अ᳘ग्र आ᳘हुतेरुदैत्त᳘स्मात्सू᳘र्यो ऽग्निहोत्रम्॥
Eggeling The Agnihotra, doubtless, is the Sun. It is because he rose in front (agre) of that offering 1, that the Agnihotra is the Sun. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स य᳘त्सायम᳘स्तमिते जुहो᳘ति॥
य᳘ इदं त᳘स्मिन्नि᳘ह सति᳘ जुहवानीत्य᳘थ य᳘त्प्रातर᳘नुदिते जुहो᳘ति य᳘ इदं त᳘स्मिन्निह᳘ सति᳘ जुहवानी᳘ति त᳘स्माद्वै सू᳘र्यो ऽग्निहोत्रमि᳘त्याहुः॥
Eggeling When he offers in the evening after sunset, he does so thinking, &amp;lsquo;I will offer, while he is here, who is this (offering);&amp;rsquo; and when he offers in the morning before sunrise, he does so thinking, &amp;lsquo;I will offer, while he is here, who is this (offering):&amp;rsquo; and for this reason, they say, the Agnihotra is the Sun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber एता᳘ ह वै᳘ देव᳘ता यो᳘ ऽस्ति॥
त᳘स्मिन्वसन्ती᳘न्द्रो यमो रा᳘जा नडो᳘ नैषिधो᳘ ऽनश्नन्त्सांगमनो᳘ ऽसन्पांसवः॥
Eggeling Verily, in him that exists 1, these deities reside, to wit, Indra, king Yama, Naḍa the Naishadha 2 (king), Anaśnat Sāṅgamana, and Asat Pāṁsava. ०२ मूलम् - Weber तद्वा᳘ एष᳘ एवे᳘न्द्रः॥
य᳘दाहवनीयो᳘ ऽथैष᳘ एव गा᳘र्हपत्यो यमो राजा᳘थैष एव᳘ नडो᳘ नैषिधो य᳘दन्वाहार्यप᳘चनस्तद्य᳘देतम᳘हरहर्दक्षिणत᳘ आह᳘रन्ति त᳘स्मादाहुर᳘हरहर्वै᳘ नडो᳘ नैषिधो᳘ यमं रा᳘जानं दक्षिणत उ᳘पनयतीति॥
Eggeling Now Indra, in truth, is the same as the Āhavanīya; and king Yama is the same as the Gārhapatya; and Naḍa Naishadha is the same as the Anvāhāryapacana (Dakshiṇa fire); and because day by day they take that (fire) to the south, therefore indeed they say that day by day Naḍa Naishadha carries king Yama 3 (further) south.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘त्र वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिः प्रजाः᳘ ससृजे॥
स य᳘त्राग्नि᳘ᳫं᳘ ससृजे स᳘ इदं᳘ जातः स᳘र्वमेव द᳘ग्धुं दध्र इ᳘त्येॗवाबिल᳘मेव ता यास्त᳘र्हि प्रजा᳘ आसुस्ता᳘ हैनᳫं स᳘म्पेष्टुं दध्रिरे सो᳘ ऽतितिक्षमाणः पु᳘रुषमेॗवाभ्ये᳘याय॥
Eggeling Now when Prajāpati, in creating living beings, created Agni, the latter, as soon as born, sought to burn everything here: and so everybody tried to get out of his way 1. The creatures then existing sought to crush him. Being unable to endure this, he went to man.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/02/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अग्नौ᳘ ह वै᳘ देवाः᳟॥
स᳘र्वान्पशून्नि᳘दधिरे ये᳘ च ग्राम्या ये᳘ चारण्या᳘ विजयं᳘ वोपप्रैष्य᳘न्तः कामचार᳘स्य वा का᳘मायायं᳘ नो गो᳘पिष्ठो गोपायदि᳘ति वा॥
Eggeling Once on a time the gods deposited with Agni all their beasts, both domestic and wild; either because they were about to engage in battle or from a desire of free scope, or because they thought that he (Agni) would protect them as the best protector. ०२ मूलम् - Weber ता᳘नु हाग्निर्नि᳘चकमे॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
