<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिः स्वर्गं᳘ लोक᳘मजिगांसत्॥
स᳘र्वे वै᳘ पश᳘वः प्रजा᳘पतिः पु᳘रुषो᳘ऽश्वो गौर᳘विरजः स᳘ एतै᳘ रूपैॗर्नाशक्नोत्स᳘ एतं व᳘योविधमात्मा᳘नमपश्यदग्निं तं व्य᳘धत्त सो᳘ऽनुपसमुह्या᳘नुपाधायो᳘दपिपतिषत्सॗ नाशक्नोत्स᳘ उपसमु᳘ह्योपधायो᳘दपतत्त᳘स्माद᳘प्येत᳘र्हि व᳘यांसि यॗदैव᳘ पक्षा᳘ उपसमू᳘हन्ते यदा प᳘त्राणि विसृजन्तेऽथो᳘त्पतितुं 1 शक्नुवन्ति॥
Eggeling Prajāpati was desirous of going up to the world of heaven; but Prajāpati, indeed, is all the (sacrificial) animals 2&amp;ndash;man, horse, bull, ram, and he-goat:&amp;ndash;by means of these forms he could not do so. He saw this bird-like body, the fire-altar, and constructed it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber यान्वै ता᳘न्त्सप्त पु᳘रुषान्॥
ए᳘कम् पु᳘रुषम᳘कुर्वन्त्स᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिरभवत्स᳘ प्रजा᳘ असृजत स᳘ प्रजाः᳘ सृॗष्ट्वोर्ध्व उ᳘दक्रामत्स᳘ एतं᳘ लोक᳘मगछद्य᳘त्रैष᳘ एतत्त᳘पतिॗ नो ह त᳘र्ह्यन्य᳘ एत᳘स्माद᳘त्र यज्ञि᳘य आस तं᳘ देवा᳘ यज्ञे᳘नैव य᳘ष्टुमध्रियन्त॥
Eggeling Now the one person which they made out of those seven persons 1 became this Prajāpati. He produced living beings (or offspring), and having produced living beings he went upwards,&amp;ndash;he went to that world where that (sun) now shines. And, indeed, there was then no other (victim) meet for sacrifice but that one (Prajāpati), and the gods set about offering him up in sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber या वा᳘ इयं वे᳘दिः सप्त᳘विधस्य॥
एषा वे᳘देर्मा᳘त्रा स᳘ देवय᳘जनमध्यवसा᳘य पू᳘र्वया द्वारा᳘ पत्नीशा᳘लम् प्रप᳘द्य गा᳘र्हपत्यायोद्धत्या᳘वोक्षति गा᳘र्हपत्यस्यो᳘द्धतात्सप्त प्रा᳘चः प्रक्रमान्प्र᳘क्रामति त᳘तः प्रा᳘ञ्चं व्यामं वि᳘मिमीते त᳘स्य म᳘ध्य आहवनी᳘यायोद्धत्या᳘वोक्षति पूर्वार्धा᳘द्व्याम᳘स्य त्रीन्प्रा᳘चः प्रक्रमान्प्र᳘क्रामति स᳘ वेद्यन्तः᳟॥
Eggeling Now this Vedi (altar-ground, viz. the Mahāvedi of the Soma-sacrifice) is just that (right) measure for the Vedi of the sevenfold 1 (fire-altar). Having fixed upon (the place for) the sacrificial ground, he enters the Patnīśāla 2 by the front (east) door, and having thrown up (the ground) for the Gārhapatya, he sprinkles it with water.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber संवत्सरो वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिः॥
अग्नि᳘रु स᳘र्वे का᳘माःॗ सोऽय᳘ᳫं᳘ संवत्सरः᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिरकामयताग्निᳫं स᳘र्वान्का᳘मानात्मा᳘नमभिसं᳘चिन्वीये᳘ति स᳘ एकशतॗधात्मा᳘नं व्य᳘धत्त स᳘ एकशतॗधात्मा᳘नं विधा᳘याग्निᳫं स᳘र्वान्का᳘मानात्मा᳘नमभिस᳘मचिनुत स स᳘र्वे का᳘मा अभवत्त᳘स्मान्न क᳘श्चन᳘ बहिर्धा का᳘मोऽभवत्त᳘स्मादाहुः संवत्सरः स᳘र्वे का᳘मा इ᳘ति न᳘ ह संवत्सरात्क᳘श्चन᳘ बहिर्धा का᳘मोऽस्ति॥
Eggeling Prajāpati, indeed, is the year, and Agni is all objects of desire. This Prajāpati, the year, desired, &amp;lsquo;May I build up for myself a body so as to contain 1 Agni, all objects of desire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अथा᳘तश्च᳘यनस्यैव᳟॥
अन्तॗरोपस᳘दौ चिनोत्येतद्वै᳘ देवा᳘ अबिभयुर्यद्वै᳘ न इम᳘मिह र᳘क्षांसि नाष्ट्रा न᳘ हन्युरि᳘ति त᳘ एताः पु᳘रोऽपश्यन्नुपस᳘द इमा᳘नेव᳘ लोका᳘निमे वै᳘ लोकाः पु᳘रस्ताः प्रा᳘पद्यन्त ताः᳘ प्रपद्या᳘भयेऽनाष्ट्र᳘ एत᳘मात्मा᳘नᳫं स᳘मस्कुर्वत त᳘थैॗवैतद्य᳘जमान एताः पु᳘रः प्रपद्या᳘भयेऽनाष्ट्र᳘ एत᳘मात्मा᳘नᳫं स᳘ᳫं᳘स्कुरुते॥
Eggeling Now as to the building itself. He builds between the two (performances of the) Upasads 1. For at that time the gods were afraid lest the fiends, the Rakshas, should destroy that (Agni&amp;rsquo;s body) of theirs (built) there 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/10/02/6/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber संवत्सरो वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिरे᳘कशतविधः॥
त᳘स्याहोरात्रा᳘ण्यर्धमासा मा᳘सा ऋत᳘वः षष्टिर्मा᳘सस्याहोरात्रा᳘णि मासि वै᳘ संवत्सर᳘स्याहोरात्रा᳘ण्याप्यन्ते च᳘तुर्विंशतिरर्धमासास्त्र᳘योदश मा᳘सास्त्र᳘य ऋत᳘वस्ताः᳘ शतं᳘ विधाः᳘ संवत्सर᳘ एॗवैकशततमी᳘ विधा᳟॥
Eggeling The one hundred and one-fold Prajāpati, doubtless, is the year, and thereto belong days and nights, half-months, months, and seasons. The days and nights of a month are sixty, and in the month, doubtless, the days and nights of the year are obtained; and there are twenty-four half-months, thirteen months, and three seasons (of four months)&amp;ndash;that makes a hundred parts, and the year itself is the one hundred and first part.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
