<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०४ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber म᳘नो ह वा᳘ अस्य सविता᳟॥
तस्मात्सावित्रं᳘ गृह्णाति पाणो᳘ ह वा᳘ अस्य सविता त᳘मेॗवास्मिन्नेत᳘त्पुर᳘स्तात्प्राणं᳘ दधाति य᳘दुपांशु᳘ गृह्णा᳘ति त᳘मेॗवास्मिन्नेत᳘त्पश्चा᳘त्प्राणं᳘ दधाति य᳘त्सावित्रं᳘ गृह्णा᳘ति ता᳘विमा᳘ उभय᳘तः प्राणौ᳘ हितौ य᳘श्चाय᳘मुप᳘रिष्टाद्य᳘श्चाध᳘स्तात्॥
Eggeling Savitr̥, forsooth, is his 1 mind: therefore he draws the Sāvitra cup. And, forsooth, Savitr̥ is his breath (vital air);&amp;ndash;when he draws the Upāṁśu cup, then he puts into him that vital air in front; and when he draws the Sāvitra cup, then he puts into him that vital air behind: thus those two vital airs on both sides are beneficial (or, put into him), both that which is above and that which is below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber सौम्ये᳘न चरु᳘णा प्र᳘चरति॥
सो᳘मो वै᳘ देवा᳘नाᳫं हविर᳘थैतत्सो᳘मायैव᳘ हवि᳘ष्क्रियते तथा᳘तः सोमो᳘ ऽनन्तर्हितो भवति चरु᳘र्भवति चरु᳘र्वै देवा᳘नाम᳘न्नमोदनो हि᳘ चरु᳘रोदनो हि᳘ प्रत्य᳘क्षम᳘न्नं त᳘स्माच्चरु᳘र्भवति॥
Eggeling He proceeds with (the offering of) Soma&amp;rsquo;s rice-pap; for Soma is the sacrificial food of the gods; and here now sacrificial food is prepared for Soma on his part; and thus Soma is not excluded therefrom. It is a rice-pap (caru), for rice-pap is food for the gods, since rice-pap is boiled rice, and boiled rice is clearly food: therefore it is a rice-pap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber पश᳘वो वै᳘ देवा᳘नां छ᳘न्दांसि॥
तद्य᳘थेद᳘म् पश᳘वो युक्ता᳘ मनुॗष्येभ्यो व᳘हन्त्येवं छ᳘न्दांसि युक्ता᳘नि देवे᳘भ्यो यज्ञं᳘ वहन्ति तद्य᳘त्र छ᳘न्दांसि देवा᳘न्त्सम᳘तर्पयन्न᳘थ छ᳘न्दांसि देवाः स᳘मतर्पयंस्तद᳘तस्तत्प्रा᳘गभूद्यच्छ᳘न्दांसि युक्ता᳘नि देवे᳘भ्यो यज्ञम᳘वाक्षुर्य᳘देनान्त्सम᳘तीतृपन्॥
Eggeling The metres, forsooth, are the (draught) cattle of the gods. Even as harnessed cattle here on earth draw for men, so do the harnessed metres draw the sacrifice for the gods. And whenever the metres gratified the gods, then the gods gratified the metres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ता᳘नि वा᳘ एता᳘नि॥
न᳘व समिष्टयजूंषि जुहोति तद्यन्न᳘व समिष्टयजूं᳘षि जुहो᳘ति न᳘व वा᳘ अमू᳘र्बहिष्पवमा᳘ने स्तोत्रि᳘या भवन्तिॗ सैॗषोभय᳘तोॗ न्यूना विरा᳘ट् प्रज᳘ननायैत᳘स्माद्वा᳘ उभय᳘तोॗ न्यूनात्प्रज᳘ननात्प्रजा᳘पतिः प्रजाः᳘ ससृज इत᳘श्चोर्ध्वा᳘ इतश्चा᳘वाचीस्त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एत᳘स्मादुभय᳘त एवॗ न्यूनात्प्रज᳘ननात्प्रजाः᳘ सृजत इत᳘श्चोर्ध्वा᳘ इतश्चा᳘वाचीः 1 ॥
Eggeling Now, it is nine Samishṭayajus 2 he offers on this occasion. The reason why he offers nine Samishṭayajus is that those stotra-verses at the Bahishpavamāna 3 chant amount to nine. Thus there is at both ends an inferior (incomplete) virāj 4, for the sake of production: it was from that same inferior (lower) source of production on both sides that Prajāpati produced the creatures,&amp;ndash;from the one (he created) the upright, and from the other those tending to the ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/04/04/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वा᳘ अवभृथ᳘मभ्य᳘वैति॥
तद्य᳘दवभृथ᳘मभ्यवै᳘ति यो वा᳘ अस्य रसो᳘ ऽभूदा᳘हुतिभ्यो वा᳘ अस्य त᳘मजीजनद᳘थैतछ᳘रीरं त᳘स्मिन्न र᳘सो ऽस्ति तन्न᳘ परा᳘स्यं त᳘दॗपो ऽभ्य᳘वहरन्ति र᳘सो वा आ᳘पस्त᳘दस्मिन्नेतं र᳘सं दधाति त᳘देनमेते᳘न र᳘सेन सं᳘गमयति त᳘देनम᳘तो जनयति स᳘ एनं जात᳘ एव स᳘ञ्जनयति तद्य᳘दॗपो ऽभ्यवह᳘रन्ति त᳘स्मादवभृथः᳟॥
Eggeling He now betakes himself to the expiatory bath (avabhr̥tha). The reason why he betakes himself to the expiatory bath is this. What vital sap there has been in him (Soma and the sacrificer), that (sap) of his he (the priest) has produced (extracted) for the offerings.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
