<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber ऋतॗव्या उ᳘पदधाति॥
ऋत᳘व एते य᳘दृतॗव्या ऋतू᳘नेॗवैतदु᳘पदधाति त᳘देतत्स᳘र्वं य᳘दृतॗव्याः संवत्सरो वा᳘ ऋतॗव्याः संवत्सर᳘ इदᳫं स᳘र्वमिद᳘मेॗवैतत्स᳘र्वमु᳘पदधात्य᳘थो प्रज᳘ननमेत᳘त्संवत्सरो वा᳘ ऋतॗव्याः संवत्सरः᳘ प्रज᳘ननम् प्रज᳘ननमेॗवैतदु᳘पदधाति॥
Eggeling He lays down two Ritavyā (seasonal bricks). The seasonal (bricks) are the same as these seasons: it is the seasons he thereby lays down. And, indeed, the seasonal ones are everything here, for the seasonal ones are the year, and the year is everything here: he thus lays down everything here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ लोकम्पृणामु᳘पदधाति॥
असौ वा᳘ आदित्यो᳘ लोकम्पृॗणैषॗ हीमां᳘लोका᳘न्पूर᳘यत्यमु᳘मेॗवैत᳘दादित्यमु᳘पदधाति ताᳫं स᳘र्वासु चि᳘तिषू᳘पदधातीमे वै᳘ लोका᳘ एताश्चि᳘तयो ऽमुं त᳘दादित्य᳘मेषु᳘ लोके᳘षु दधाति त᳘स्मादेष स᳘र्वेभ्य एॗवैभ्यो᳘ लोके᳘भ्यस्तपति॥
Eggeling He then lays down a Lokampr̥ṇā 1 (space-filling brick); the Lokampr̥ṇā, doubtless, is yonder sun, for he fills these worlds: it is thus yonder sun he thereby sets up. He lays down this (Lokampr̥ṇā) in all the (five) layers, for those layers are these (three) worlds 2: he thus places the sun in (all) these worlds, whence he shines for all these worlds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ पु᳘रीषं नि᳘वपति॥
मांसं वै पु᳘रीषम् मांसे᳘नैॗवैनमेतत्प्र᳘छादयती᳘ष्टका उपधायास्यी᳘ष्टका अ᳘स्थि त᳘न्मांसैः सं᳘छादयति॥
Eggeling He now throws loose soil (on the layer); for the loose soil means flesh: he thus covers him (Agni) with flesh. [He does so] after having laid down the bricks;&amp;ndash;the bricks are the bone: he thus covers the bone with flesh. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ स्वयमातृणा᳘यामा᳘वपति॥
प्राणो वै᳘ स्वयमातृणा᳘न्नम् पु᳘रीषम् प्राणे तद᳘न्नं दधाति ते᳘न स᳘र्वमात्मा᳘नम् प्र᳘छादयति त᳘म्माद्य᳘त्प्राणे᳘ ऽन्नं धीय᳘ते स᳘र्वमात्मा᳘नम᳘वति स᳘र्वमात्मा᳘नमनुॗव्येति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/08/07/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘थ स्वयमातृणा᳘सु सा᳘मानि गायति॥
इमे वै᳘ लोकाः᳘ स्वयमातृणास्ता᳘ एताः श᳘र्करास्ता᳘ देवा᳘ उपधा᳘यैतादृ᳘शीरेॗवापश्यन्य᳘थैताः शु᳘ष्काः श᳘र्कराः॥
Eggeling On the (three) naturally-perforated (bricks) he (the Sacrificer) sings sāmans; for the naturally-perforated ones are these (three) worlds; and they are just these (ordinary) stones. The gods, having laid them down, saw them as such: that they were dry stones.
०२ मूलम् - Weber ते ऽब्रुवन्॥
उ᳘प त᳘ज्जानीत य᳘थैषु᳘ लोके᳘षु र᳘मसुपजी᳘वनं द᳘धामे᳘तिॗ ते ऽब्रुवंश्चेत᳘यध्वमि᳘ति चि᳘तिमिछते᳘ति वाव त᳘दब्रुवंस्त᳘दिछत य᳘थैषु᳘ लोके᳘षु र᳘समुपजी᳘वनं द᳘धामे᳘ति॥</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
