<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अरण्योरग्नी᳘ समारो᳘ह्य॥
सेनाॗन्यो गृहा᳘न्परे᳘त्याग्नये᳘ ऽनीकवते ऽष्ठा᳘कपालम् पुरोडा᳘शं नि᳘र्वपत्यग्निर्वै᳘ देव᳘तानाम᳘नीकᳫं से᳘नाया वै᳘ सेनानीर᳘नीकं त᳘स्मादग्नये᳘ ऽनीकवत एतद्वा᳘ अस्यै᳘कं र᳘त्नं य᳘त्सेनानीस्त᳘स्मा एॗवैते᳘न सूय᳘ते तᳫं स्वम᳘नपक्रमिणं कुरुते त᳘स्य हि᳘रण्यं द᳘क्षिणाग्नेयो वा᳘ एष᳘ यज्ञो᳘ भवत्यग्ने रे᳘तो हि᳘रण्यं त᳘स्माद्धिरण्यं द᳘क्षिणा॥
Eggeling Having taken up both (the Gārhapatya and Āhavanīya) fires on the two kindling-sticks 1, he goes to the house of the Commander of the army, and prepares a cake on eight potsherds for Agni Anīkavat; for Agni is the head (anīka) of the gods, and the commander is the head of the army: hence for Agni Anīkavat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber उप᳘रिष्टाद्र᳘त्नानाᳫं सौमारौद्रे᳘ण यजते॥
स᳘ श्वेता᳘यै श्वेत᳘वत्सायै प᳘यसि शृतो᳘ भवति तद्य᳘दुप᳘रिष्टाद्र᳘त्नानाᳫं सौमारौद्रे᳘ण य᳘जते॥
Eggeling After the &amp;lsquo;jewels&amp;rsquo; he offers (a pap) to Soma and Rudra. It is cooked in milk from a white (cow) which has a white calf. And as to why, after the &amp;lsquo;jewels,&amp;rsquo; he offers (a pap) to Soma and Rudra. ०२ मूलम् - Weber स्वर्भानुर्ह वा᳘ आसुरः᳟॥
सू᳘र्यं त᳘मसा विव्याध स त᳘मसा विद्धो न व्य᳘रोचत त᳘स्य सोमारुद्रा᳘वेॗवैतत्तमो᳘ ऽपाहताᳫं स᳘ एषो᳘ ऽपहतपाप्मा तपति त᳘थो एॗवैष᳘ एतत्त᳘मः प्र᳘विशत्येतं᳘ वा त᳘मः प्र᳘विशति य᳘दयज्ञिया᳘न्यज्ञे᳘न प्रस᳘जत्ययज्ञियान्वा᳘ एत᳘द्यज्ञे᳘न प्र᳘सजति शूद्रा᳘ᳫं᳘स्त्वद्या᳘ᳫं᳘स्त्वत्त᳘स्य सोमारुद्रा᳘वेॗवैतत्तमो᳘ ऽपहतः सो᳘ ऽपहतपाप्मैव᳘ दीक्षते तद्य᳘छ्वेता᳘यै श्वेत᳘वत्सायै प᳘यसि शृतो भ᳘वति कृष्णं वै त᳘मस्तत्तमो᳘ ऽपहन्ति त᳘स्यैॗषैव᳘ श्वेता᳘ श्वेत᳘वत्सा द᳘क्षिणा॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वै᳘ दीक्षते॥
स᳘ उपवसॗथे ऽग्नीषोमी᳘यम् पशुमा᳘लभते त᳘स्य वप᳘या प्रच᳘र्याग्नीसोमी᳘यमे᳘कादशकपालम् पुरोडा᳘शम् नि᳘र्वपति तद᳘नु देवॗस्वाᳫं 1 हवीं᳘षि नि᳘रुप्यन्ते॥
Eggeling He performs the initiation ceremony. On the day of preparation he seizes the victim for Agni and Soma. Having performed the offering of the omentum thereof; he prepares a cake on eleven potsherds for Agni and Soma 2. Thereupon the offerings of the Divine Quickeners (Devasū) are prepared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber स वा᳘ अपः स᳘म्भरति॥
तद्य᳘दपः᳘ सम्भ᳘रति वीर्यं᳘ वा आ᳘पो वीर्य᳘मेॗवैतद्र᳘समपाᳫं स᳘म्भरति॥
Eggeling He collects (various kinds of) water. The reason why he collects water, is that&amp;ndash;water being vigour&amp;ndash;he thereby collects vigour, the essence of die waters. ०२ मूलम् - Weber औ᳘दुम्बरे पा᳘त्रे॥
अ᳘न्नं वा᳘ ऊर्गुदुम्ब᳘र ऊॗर्जो ऽन्ना᳘द्यस्या᳘वरुद्ध्यै त᳘स्मादौ᳘दुम्बरे पा᳘त्रे॥
Eggeling In a vessel of udumbara wood,&amp;ndash;the udumbara (ficus glomerata) being sustenance, (that is) food&amp;mdash;for the obtainment of sustenance, food: hence in an udumbara vessel (he mixes the different liquids).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/05/03/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber तं वै मा᳘ध्यदिने स᳘वने ऽभि᳘षिञ्चति॥
एष वै᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिर्य᳘ एष᳘ यज्ञ᳘स्ताय᳘ते य᳘स्मादिमाः᳘ प्रजाः प्र᳘जाता एत᳘म्वेवा᳘प्येतर्ह्य᳘नु प्र᳘जायन्ते त᳘देनम् मध्यत᳘ एॗवैत᳘स्य प्रजा᳘पतेर्द᳘धाति मध्यतः᳘ सुवति॥
Eggeling He consecrates him at the midday Soma-feast. Now Prajāpati is that sacrifice which is here performed, and whence these creatures have been produced,&amp;ndash;and so they are even now produced after this one: he thus places him in the very middle of that Prajāpati, and consecrates him in the middle.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
