<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०२ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/1/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिर्देवे᳘भ्यो यज्ञान्व्या᳘दिशत्॥
स᳘ आत्म᳘न्नश्वमेध᳘मधत्त ते᳘ देवाः᳘ प्रजा᳘पतिमब्रुवन्नेष वै᳘ यज्ञो य᳘दश्वमेधो᳘ऽपि नो᳘ऽत्रास्तु भग इ᳘ति ते᳘भ्य एता᳘नन्नहोमा᳘न्कल्पयद्य᳘दन्नहोमा᳘न्जुहोति देवा᳘नेव त᳘त्प्रीणाति॥
Eggeling Prajāpati assigned the sacrifices to the gods; the Aśvamedha he kept for himself. The gods said to him, &amp;lsquo;Surely, this&amp;ndash;to wit, the Aśvamedha&amp;ndash;is a sacrifice: let us have a share in that also.&amp;rsquo; He contrived these Anna-homas (food-oblations) for them: thus when he performs the Annahomas, it is the gods he thereby gratifies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/10/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber य᳘दसिपथा᳘न्कल्प᳘यन्ति॥
से᳘तुमेव त᳘ᳫं᳘ संक्र᳘मणं य᳘जमानः कुरुते स्वर्ग᳘स्य लोक᳘स्य स᳘मष्ट्यै॥
Eggeling When they prepare the knife-paths, the Sacrificer makes for himself that passage across, a bridge, for the attainment of the heavenly world. ०२ मूलम् - Weber सूची᳘भिः कल्पयन्ति॥
वि᳘शो वै᳘ सूॗच्यो राष्ट्र᳘मश्वमेधो वि᳘शं चैॗवास्मिन्राष्ट्रं᳘ च समी᳘ची दधति हिरण्यम᳘य्यो भवन्ति त᳘स्योक्तम् ब्रा᳘ह्मणम्॥
Eggeling They prepare them by means of needles; the needles, doubtless, are the people 1 (clans), and the Aśvamedha is the royal power: they thus supply him with people and royal power combined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/11/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरकामयत॥
महान्भूयान्त्स्यामि᳘ति स᳘ एता᳘वश्वमेधे महिमा᳘नौ ग्र᳘हावपश्यत्ता᳘वजुहोत्त᳘तो वै स᳘ महान्भू᳘यानभवत्स यः᳘ काम᳘येत महान्भू᳘यान्त्स्यामि᳘ति स᳘ एता᳘वश्वमेधे᳘ महिमा᳘नौ ग्र᳘हौ जुहुयान्महा᳘न्हैव भू᳘यान्भवति॥
Eggeling Prajāpati desired, &amp;lsquo;Would that I were great, and more numerous!&amp;rsquo; He perceived those two Mahiman (greatness) cups of Soma at the Aśvamedha; he offered them; and thereby, indeed, became great and more numerous: hence whosoever should desire to become great, and more numerous, let him offer up those two Mahiman cups of Soma at the Aśvamedha; and he indeed becomes great and more numerous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/2/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber राजा वा᳘ एष᳘ यज्ञा᳘नां य᳘दश्वमेधः᳟॥
य᳘जमानो वा᳘ अश्द्यज्ञमा᳘रभतेवमेधो य᳘जमानो यज्ञो यद᳘श्वे पशू᳘न्नियुन᳘क्ति यज्ञ᳘ एव त᳟॥
Eggeling Verily, this&amp;ndash;to wit, the Aśvamedha&amp;ndash;is the king of sacrifices. But, indeed, the Aśvamedha is the Sacrificer, (for) the sacrifice is the Sacrificer: when he (the priest) binds victims to the horse (or, at the horse-sacrifice), he then, indeed, takes hold 1 of the sacrifice at the sacrifice. ०२ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘श्वं तूपरं᳘ गोमृगमि᳘ति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/3/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber देवा वा᳘ अश्वमेधे प᳘वमानं॥
स्वर्गं᳘ लोकं न प्रा᳘जानंस्तम᳘श्वः प्रा᳘जानाद्य᳘दश्वमेधे᳘ऽश्वेन प᳘वमानाय स᳘र्पन्ति स्वर्ग᳘स्य लोक᳘स्य प्र᳘ज्ञात्यै पु᳘छमन्वा᳘रभन्ते स्वर्ग᳘स्यैव᳘ लोक᳘स्य स᳘मष्ट्यै न वै᳘ मनुष्यः᳘ स्वर्गं᳘ लोकम᳘ञ्जसा वेदा᳘श्वो वै᳘ स्वर्गं᳘ लोकम᳘ञ्जसा वेद॥
Eggeling Now, the gods did not know the Pavamāna 1 at the Aśvamedha to be the heavenly world, but the horse knew it. When, at the Aśvamedha, they glide along 2 with the horse for the Pavamāna (-stotra), it is for getting to know (the way to) the heavenly world; and they hold on to the horse&amp;rsquo;s tail, in order to reach the heavenly world; for man does not rightly know (the way to) the heavenly world, but the horse does rightly know it</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/4/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरकामयत॥
उभौ᳘ लोका᳘वभि᳘जयेयं देवलोकं᳘ च मनुष्यलोकं चे᳘ति स᳘ एता᳘न्पशू᳘नपश्यद्ग्राम्यां᳘श्च ताना᳘लभत तै᳘रिमौ᳘ लोकाव᳘वारुन्द्ध ग्राम्यै᳘रेव᳘ पशु᳘भिरिमं᳘ लोकमवा᳘रुन्द्धारण्यै᳘रमु᳘मयं वै᳘ लोको᳘ मनुष्यलोको᳘ऽथासौ᳘ देवलोको य᳘द्ग्राम्या᳘न्पशू᳘नाल᳘भत इम᳘मेव तै᳘र्लोकं य᳘जमानो᳘ऽवरुन्द्धे य᳘दारण्या᳘नमुं तैः᳟॥
Eggeling Prajāpati desired, &amp;lsquo;Would that I might gain both worlds, the world of the gods, and the world of men.&amp;rsquo; He saw those beasts, the tame and the wild ones; he seized them, and by means of them took possession of these two worlds: by means of the tame beasts he took possession of this (terrestrial) world, and by means of the wild beasts of yonder (world); for this world is the world of men, and yonder world is the world of the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/5/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber प्रजा᳘पतिरश्वमेध᳘मसृजत᳟᳟॥
सोऽस्मात्सृष्टः प᳘राङैत्स᳘ पङ्क्ति᳘र्भूत्वा᳘ संवत्सरम् प्रा᳘विशॗत्तेऽर्धमासा᳘ अभवंस्त᳘म् पञ्चदशि᳘भिरनुप्रा᳘युङ्क्त त᳘माप्नोत्त᳘माप्त्वा᳘ पञ्चदशि᳘भिर᳘वारुन्द्धार्धमासा᳘नां वा᳘ एषा᳘ प्रतिमा य᳘त्पञ्चदशि᳘नो य᳘त्पञ्चदशि᳘न आल᳘भतेऽर्धमासा᳘नेव तैर्य᳘जमानो᳘ऽवरुन्द्धे॥
Eggeling Prajāpati poured forth the life-sap of the horse (aśva-medha); when poured forth it went from him. Having become fivefold 1 it entered the year, and they (the five parts) became those half-months 2. He followed it up by means of the fifteenfold (sets of victims 3), and found it; and having found it, he took possession of it by means of the fifteenfold ones; for, indeed, they&amp;ndash;to wit, the fifteenfold (sets)&amp;ndash;are a symbol of the half-months, and when he seizes the fifteenfold ones, it is the half-months the Sacrificer thereby takes possession of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/6/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber युञ्ज᳘न्ति ब्रध्न᳘मरुषं च᳘रन्तमि᳘ति॥
असौ वा᳘ आदित्यो᳘ ब्रॗध्नोऽरुॗषोऽमु᳘मेवाॗस्मा आदित्यं᳘ युनक्ति स्वर्ग᳘स्य लोक᳘स्य स᳘मष्ट्यै॥
Eggeling [He puts the horse to the chariot 1 with Vāj. S. XXIII, 5], &amp;lsquo;They harness the ruddy bay, moving (round the moveless: the lights shine in the heavens);&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;the ruddy bay, doubtless, is yonder sun: it is yonder sun he harnesses for him, for the gaining of the heavenly world.
०२ मूलम् - Weber त᳘दाहुः॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/7/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber नि᳘युक्तेषु पशु᳘षु॥
प्रो᳘क्षणीरध्वर्युरा᳘दत्ते᳘ऽश्वम् प्रोक्षिष्य᳘न्नन्वारब्धे य᳘जमान आ᳘ध्वरिकं य᳘जुरनुद्रुत्या᳘श्वमेधिकं य᳘जुः प्र᳘तिपद्यते॥
Eggeling When the victims have been bound (to the stakes), the Adhvaryu takes the sprinkling-water in order to sprinkle the horse. Whilst the Sacrificer holds on to him behind, he (in sprinkling the horse) runs rapidly through the formula used at the Soma-sacrifice 1, and then commences the one for the Aśvamedha. ०२ मूलम् - Weber वायु᳘ष्ट्वा पचतै᳘रवत्वि᳘ति॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/8/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber देवा वा उ᳘दञ्चः॥
स्वर्गं᳘ लोकं न प्रा᳘जानंस्तम᳘श्वः प्रा᳘जानाद्यद᳘श्वेनो᳘दञ्चो यन्ति स्वर्ग᳘स्य लोक᳘स्य प्र᳘ज्ञात्यै वा᳘सोऽधिवासᳫं हि᳘रण्यमित्य᳘श्वायो᳘पस्तृणन्ति य᳘थाॗ नान्य᳘स्मै पश᳘वे त᳘स्मिन्नेनम᳘धि सं᳘ज्ञपयन्त्यन्यै᳘रेॗवैनं त᳘त्पशु᳘भिर्व्या᳘कुर्वन्ति॥
Eggeling Now the gods, when going upwards, did not know (the way to) the heavenly world, but the horse knew it: when they go upwards with the horse, it is in order to know (the way to) the heavenly world. &amp;lsquo;A cloth, an upper cloth, and gold,&amp;rsquo; this 1 is what they spread out for the horse 2: thereon they quiet (slay) it, as (is done) for no other victim; and thus they separate it from the other victims.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/sarva-prastutiH/13/02/9/</guid>
      <description>०१ मूलम् - Weber अ᳘प वा᳘ एत᳘स्मात्॥
श्री राष्ट्रं᳘ क्रामतिॗ योऽश्वमेधे᳘न य᳘जते॥
Eggeling But, indeed, that glory, royal power, passes away from him who performs the Aśvamedha. ०२ मूलम् - Weber ऊर्ध्वा᳘मेनामु᳘छ्रापये᳘ति॥
श्रीर्वै᳘ राष्ट्र᳘मश्वमेधः श्रि᳘यमेॗवास्मै राष्ट्र᳘मूर्ध्वमु᳘छ्रयति॥
Eggeling [The Udgātr̥ 1 says concerning the king&amp;rsquo;s favourite wife, Vāj. S. XXIII, 26,] &amp;lsquo;Raise her upwards 2,&amp;rsquo;&amp;ndash;the Aśvamedha, doubtless, is that glory, royal power: that glory, royal power, he thus raises for him (the Sacrificer) upward.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
